<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great interest of states &amp; kingdomes. The second part. A sermon preached on a publike thanksgiving, on the 12th. of May, 1646. at Botolphs Alders-gate: and after (upon the desire of some friends) enlarged at Pauls Church in Covent-garden, on the Lords Day, May 17th. 1646. / By Simon Ford, minister of the Gospel at Puddle-Towne in Dorcet-shire.</title>
            <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E356_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860709</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860709</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112834</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84686)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112834)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E356[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great interest of states &amp; kingdomes. The second part. A sermon preached on a publike thanksgiving, on the 12th. of May, 1646. at Botolphs Alders-gate: and after (upon the desire of some friends) enlarged at Pauls Church in Covent-garden, on the Lords Day, May 17th. 1646. / By Simon Ford, minister of the Gospel at Puddle-Towne in Dorcet-shire.</title>
                  <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 33, 36-37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Wilson, for Francis Eglesfield, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Marigold.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>There is no record of a first part, though Thomas Goodwin preached a sermon of the same name (Wing G1246A) the previous February.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 6th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CV, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112834:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GREAT INTEREST OF STATES &amp; KINGDOMES.</p>
            <p>The Second Part.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached on a Publike Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, on the 12<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1646. at <hi>Botolphs Alders-gate:</hi> And after (upon the deſire of ſome friends) enlarged at <hi>Pauls</hi> Church in <hi>Covent-garden,</hi> on the Lords Day, <hi>May</hi> 17<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1646.</p>
            <p>By SIMON FORD, Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Puddle-Towne</hi> in <hi>Dorcet-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 105. 15.</bibl>
               <p>—<hi>He rebuked Kings for their ſakes,</hi> Saying—<hi>Doe my Prophets no harme.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by W. WILSON, for <hi>Francis Eglesfield,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, at the Signe of the Marigold. 1646.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112834:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112834:2"/>
            <head>To the truely Noble, and publike-hearted PATRIOT, SIR WILLIAM WALLER, Knight, A Member of the Honourable Houſe of <hi>COMMONS.</hi> This Sermon, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Prayers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT this plaine Sermon <hi>caſts it ſelfe,</hi> upon your <hi>Patronage;</hi> the <hi>Subject</hi> it handles, juſtly <hi>challengeth</hi> at my hands. For, (beſides that I am a <hi>debtor</hi> to your ſelfe mainly, under God, for that ranke, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be (though of the <hi>loweſt Forme)</hi> which I have had in the Schooles, and now have in the <hi>Society</hi> of the <hi>Prophets;)</hi> it is an obligation to me, that I ſee you (among your <hi>many imployments</hi> of meerely <hi>publike importance)</hi> ſo cordially carefull of preſerving <hi>unviolated</hi> this <hi>Intereſt of Intereſts,</hi> the maine Subject of theſe Meditations.</p>
            <p>Sir, 'tis to me, and to all thoſe whoſe <hi>glory</hi> 'tis indeed, (though it is now, in ſome mouthes, grown a <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Scorne)</hi> to be <hi>old Diſciples,</hi> that is, <hi>tried Saints,</hi> a matter
<pb facs="tcp:112834:3"/> of praiſe to that good God that <hi>principles</hi> &amp; <hi>proſpers</hi> you, to behold the <hi>evenneſs</hi> of your <hi>ſpirit</hi> carryed out in all conditions to the proſecution of <hi>publike Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts</hi> with the ſame height of <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> &amp; <hi>fervency.</hi> To inſtance only in a few particulars; ſeeing I know ſuch a <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> (if enlarged as it might be) though it might be very <hi>welcome</hi> to all <hi>underſtanding,</hi> and <hi>well-affected</hi> Readers beſides; yet, to you it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ill, whoſe (in ſome ſenſe) <hi>ſupererogatory</hi> piece of <hi>worth</hi> it is, <hi>to be willing to doe well, without being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be told of it.</hi> Sir, we remember how in the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall part</hi> of this Ages <hi>imployment,</hi> (notwithſtanding continuall oppoſitions <hi>of the firſt Magnitude,</hi> both at <hi>home</hi> and <hi>abroad,</hi> the Lord bleſſed your <hi>ſmall inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable numbers</hi> of the <hi>worſt furniſhed,</hi> and <hi>leaſt pai'd</hi> ſouldiers of any, with <hi>ſucceſſes,</hi> which the <hi>judgment</hi> of the <hi>late yeares</hi> thought ſomewhat <hi>bordering</hi> on <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles;</hi> that you were the <hi>kingdomes Wall of Braſſe</hi> (next our God) at <hi>Alton, Arundell,</hi> and <hi>Cheriton field:</hi> and (by Gods ſpeciall, never-to-be-forgotten, goodneſſe) a principall meanes of its preſervation: that you cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obeyed the call of the <hi>Houſes,</hi> in a <hi>calme reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of your <hi>Forces</hi> and <hi>Command,</hi> and ſate downe one of the chief <hi>Self-denying Members,</hi> without <hi>capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> for <hi>pay,</hi> or <hi>giving</hi> any manner of <hi>encouragement</hi> to, or ſo much as <hi>accepting</hi> of the <hi>deſires</hi> of the <hi>ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery,</hi> eaſie enough to have been induced to <hi>follow ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi> and to <hi>mutiny</hi> for a <hi>diſpenſation</hi> of the <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of your <hi>command,</hi> as the ſtirrings of <hi>many quieted</hi> by your <hi>wiſedome,</hi> and the <hi>wet eyes</hi> of <hi>more abundantly drencht</hi> by their <hi>affection,</hi> did largely teſtifie at your <hi>departure.</hi> And we hope ſhall remember to Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall praiſe, &amp; your perpetuall glory, that now in your
<pb facs="tcp:112834:3"/> meerely <hi>repreſentative Capacity</hi> you keep ſteddy to your <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Honour, voting</hi> and acting from an <hi>impulſive</hi> within your <hi>owne breaſt,</hi> without thoſe <hi>Springs</hi> and <hi>Wires,</hi> and <hi>weights,</hi> that only keep many mens <hi>motions regular;</hi> that in theſe dayes great <hi>juſtles</hi> of <hi>ſeverally ingaged Parties,</hi> you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſtill the ſame <hi>unbyaſſed, Covenant-ſpirit,</hi> and do not promote with a <hi>politick compliance,</hi> or <hi>act</hi> with a <hi>tumultuous precipitancy,</hi> the deſignes of <hi>Jeſuiticall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries,</hi> whether of the <hi>line</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> or of <hi>Munſter,</hi> who <hi>concur</hi> in an endeavour of ſetting a <hi>new fire</hi> on three kingdomes, ere the <hi>old</hi> be fully <hi>extinguiſhed,</hi> for no other <hi>ends</hi> (that I know) but that (like that <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Nero)</hi> they may ſing <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the heat, &amp;c. or <hi>ſee</hi> more <hi>new light</hi> in the <hi>flames</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>But above all, that which renders you moſt <hi>precious</hi> in the eyes of all that <hi>hate Babel,</hi> is; your <hi>ſetled</hi> and <hi>conſtant affection</hi> to the <hi>Prophets of God</hi> (now the <hi>ſcorne</hi> of this (as * one well calls it) <hi>Chriſt-glutted,</hi> and <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Shepherd</hi> in his <hi>Sound Beleever.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Goſpel-glutted Age,</hi> and trampled upon <hi>on all hands,</hi> as the very <hi>off-ſcouring of all things)</hi> of which, you dayly give ſuch ample <hi>teſtimony,</hi> that (I dare aſſure you,) you have a large ſhare in <hi>Prophets Prayers,</hi> and I hope will one day have (<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 41.</note> according to the promiſe) a liberall portion of the <hi>Prophets reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Sir, for the future, whatſoever <hi>diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> you meet withall in the <hi>ſame good way,</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>him</hi> (I pray you) who <hi>endured the contradiction of ſinners,</hi> and yet grew not <hi>weary</hi> of his <hi>worke,</hi> but <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed</hi> it on to <hi>perfection</hi> in deſpight of all the <hi>powers of darkneſſe.</hi> Go you, and do likewiſe: Tell the <hi>humorous</hi> world, that (although its <hi>experienced fickleneſſe</hi> gives you little reaſon to build much upon its conſtancy,
<pb facs="tcp:112834:4"/> yet) you will add <hi>one wonder</hi> more to its <hi>ſeven,</hi> to wit, <hi>that you are in this Lunatick age; the ſame man you were a yeare ſince.</hi> And I hope, when <hi>England</hi> hath recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red its <hi>wits</hi> againe, when its <hi>Platonick yeare</hi> comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and <hi>Errors Circle</hi> is run quite through, ſo that <hi>caſt Truthes,</hi> like <hi>ſuper-annuated factions,</hi> ſhall <hi>return.</hi> and become <hi>New-light</hi> again, (which I doubt not but it will be in time) it wil then ſee cauſe to acknowledge (to your honour, and theirs (who have with you) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <hi>grace</hi> to be kept <hi>faithfull)</hi> that thoſe who have <hi>ſtood</hi> to their <hi>places</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> in all this <hi>change,</hi> have done far better then thoſe <hi>fallen Angels</hi> among us, who have <hi>left their Stations,</hi> and <hi>run</hi> the <hi>ring</hi> of <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions,</hi> and <hi>parties,</hi> ſo long, to <hi>returne</hi> at laſt, to the <hi>Point</hi> from whence they begun their <hi>irregular motion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have onely one word more, and that concerns this homely <hi>piece</hi> of mine. Sir, in this <hi>Dedication,</hi> I hope you wil look upon <hi>my deſire to teſtifie to the world how far you have obliged me;</hi> and the <hi>maine motive</hi> that put me upon the thoughts of it; and accordingly accept it. Yet I muſt acknowledge that I have withall a <hi>plot</hi> upon your <hi>name,</hi> being perſwaded, that (for its ſake in the <hi>front</hi> of this <hi>Epiſtle)</hi> many <hi>tranſient</hi> Readers may be perhaps <hi>ſtayed</hi> and <hi>intreated</hi> to <hi>read</hi> beyond the <hi>Title-page,</hi> ſome of whom might elſe perchance <hi>lay</hi> it <hi>by</hi> for a <hi>Pamphlet ſick of the extravagancies of this Age,</hi> it being owned by ſo <hi>obſcure</hi> an <hi>Author</hi> as is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Yours, and the Churches <hi>weake,</hi> but (to his power) <hi>faithfull</hi> Servant in the Goſpel, S. FORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112834:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, though this <hi>ſecond Part</hi> had not the honour to be ſo publike from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> as its elder brother, the <hi>firſt,</hi> had; yet the judgement and importunity of ſome <hi>well affected to me,</hi> and the threatnings, and miſ-reports of others <hi>diſ-affected to it and mee,</hi> have made it no leſſe publike from the <hi>Preſſe.</hi> And yet (as thou maiſt perceive by my addreſſes in the Application) it was ſufficiently publique in the preaching too; there being as great a number of the Kingdomes and Cities <hi>Worthies</hi> preſent, as any Congregation, that I know, in <hi>London,</hi> affords upon the <hi>Lords Day.</hi> I confeſſe that I am one of the youngeſt ſonnes of the Prophets, which I plead for; and therefore I am apt enough to acknowledge againſt my ſelfe, that I believe, this ſubject might have been farre better handled by many thouſands of my Fathers and brethren: But my plea muſt be that of <hi>Elihu,</hi> Job 32. <hi>I waited, but they ſpake not, &amp;c.</hi> verſe 16. and I could not be guilty of ſo much unrighteouſneſſe, as the detaining of ſo neceſſary a truth, when God had put it in my heart, would have invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me in.</p>
            <p>I have made ſome <hi>Alterations</hi> in <hi>Method,</hi> and ſome <hi>Additions</hi> in <hi>Matter,</hi> ſince I preached it; in the former I have pleaſed my ſelfe; in the latter, I have ſatisfied (I hope) divers of my hearers, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned that touch of controverſie in the Concluſion; in which, I thought it onely neceſſary, to fling a few pebbles of exceptions at that <hi>Goliah</hi> of the Anabaptiſts, and rigid Separatiſts, (their Argument for Separation drawne from our (falſely called Antichriſtian) Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery) which, I am confident, any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaged Reader will ſay: have ſo farre entred its Brazen <hi>forehead,</hi> as to lay it flat; and though it may ſtruggle for life in ſome after-cavills, (which I expect from the
<pb facs="tcp:112834:5"/> hoſt of that <hi>Phili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>im)</hi> yet it will never ſtrut againe with its ſpeare like a <hi>Weavers Beame,</hi> and <hi>defie</hi> the Prophets of God, the Miniſtery of all the Reformed Churches, or <hi>the hoſts of the living God,</hi> all the Saints that have been begotten, fed, &amp; tranſlated to glory under it.</p>
            <p>I have not medled with any other, becauſe they all depend on the ſucceſſe of this; and this being over-throwne, they will bee contented (like ſome Heathen Nobles, of whom Travellers report, that they are killed when their King dyes, to doe him ſervice in another world) to fall to ground, and be buried with it.</p>
            <p>I am (I bleſſe God) prepared to <hi>receive</hi> the great and furious <hi>charges</hi> of being too bitter againſt, and grieving the Saints. The Father tells me, 'tis no more than I muſt expect. <hi>What wonder,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if when I ſeek my Maſters loſt ſheep, I am now and then ſcratched by the Briar-buſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of detracting tongues <note n="a" place="margin">Quid mirum, ſi cum—do mini mei oves perditas dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter inquiro, ſpinoſarum lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarum v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hus laceror! <hi>Aug. cont. Peti. lib.</hi> 30.</note>! <hi>And ſhall ſtil reſolve with that other Father,</hi> never to hunt for the good of being eſteemed milde, with ſo great an evill, as the loſſe of truth</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Naz. Orat.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>I hope, I ſhall ſtand the firſt charge of theſe, under the ſhelter of that Buckler, which the Apoſtle hands to me in the command, <hi>Rebuke them ſharply, &amp;c.</hi> Titus 1. 13.</p>
            <p>To the laſt I returne this: That they do give a very weak evidence, that they are Saints, that will be grieved to heare the Miniſterie, by which they were called to be Saints, vindicated from the calumnies of ('tis to be feared, but) pretended ones.</p>
            <p>And I muſt by the way tell them, that thus object; that, I pray God, they have no more to anſwer, for <hi>grieving Prophets,</hi> (a greater ſinne (I am ſure) though leſſe taken notice of) then I have, for <hi>grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, if Saints will be grieved, when <hi>they</hi> are laſhed, <hi>who are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Saints to the diſgrace of Saintſhip;</hi> I am not Maſter of their paſſions: and I am ſorry ſo ſlight and unconcerning a Matter, will trouble them; and more ſorry they ſhould thereby bring themſelves under the ſuſpition of being guilty of that, which they cannot endure ſhould be touched. I have no more to Preface at this time, but that I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, as far as becomes a Goſpel Prophet, S. FORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112834:5"/>
            <head>THE GREAT INTEREST OF STATES and KINGDOMES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 105. 15.</bibl>
               <q>—<hi>And doe my Prophets no harme.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS Pſalme ſeemes to be intended for an <hi>Euchariſticall commemoration</hi> of Gods mercies to <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe mercies concerne</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Their <hi>Riſe; (Originall</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies) &amp; theſe in
<list>
                     <item>1. Gods <hi>Choyſe</hi> of them. v. 6, 7. <note place="margin">The Palme taken aſunder.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Gods <hi>Covenant</hi> with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. v. 8. 9, 10, 11.</item>
                     <item>3. Gods protecting <hi>Providence</hi> over them. v. 12, 13, 14, 15.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Their <hi>Race;</hi> in the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whereof they are againe led into
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Egypt</hi> from the 15. to the 33. in which are ſpecified
<list>
                           <item>1. Gods <hi>Proviſion</hi> for them from v. 15. to 24</item>
                           <item>2. Gods <hi>Propagation,</hi> and increaſing of them. v. 24.</item>
                           <item>3. Gods <hi>Miraculous work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our enlargement</hi> to them, from v. 24. to 39. And this mercy ſo great, tis repeated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, v. 43.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Wilderneſſe</hi> from 39. v. to the 43.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Caraan.</hi> v. 44. 45.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe words are a part of the <hi>third</hi> branch of the <hi>firſt</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Iſraels <hi>Originall-mercyes.</hi> And the piece of <hi>Originall-mercy</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112834:6"/> held forth in them, is cut out by the Hiſtoricall Narration of a ſpeciall protection of <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 12. and 20. and <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 26. whither I muſt referre you.</p>
            <p>In the whole verſe there is a double charge given by God <note place="margin">Parts of the Text.</note> unto <hi>thoſe Kings,</hi> in whoſe power it lay, to injure the travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Patriarchs.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Touch them not.</item>
               <item>Harme them not.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The perſons concerning whom tis given are deſcribed by a double Character
<list>
                  <item>Anointed.</item>
                  <item>Prophets.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Except you may perhaps thinke the laſt of both <hi>exegeticall</hi> to the firſt, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>De more Pſaltes poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ori hemiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chio explicat prius; tangere enim Chriſtos Dei non eſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetis maligna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. A Lap. in Heb. c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Touch not.</hi> i. e. <hi>Harme not, touch not unjuſtly; Mine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed,</hi> i. e. <hi>My Prophets;</hi> in which I ſhall not contend.</p>
            <p>There is a ſufficient foundation to beare the building which I meane to raiſe upon theſe words, in that the charge here gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven concernes the ſame perſons, in both branches; and ſo, as <note n="a" place="margin">Et ſi nondum unctionis erat uſus, Propheta tamen id reipſa fuiſſe in Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamo, &amp;c. teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quod Deus in Ceremoniis legalibus poſtea oſtendit. Calv. ad locum.</note> 
               <hi>Anointed Prophets,</hi> as well as <hi>Anointed Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the former branch of this <hi>Charge,</hi> concerning the perſons under its <hi>Character,</hi> there hath beene enough ſpoken in a more ſolemne Auditory by a <note n="*" place="margin">M. Th. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win at a ſolemn Faſt, <hi>Feb.</hi> 25. before the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> reverend Brother (if not too much at this ſeaſon, by reaſon of the ſtrange pleas of the <hi>Advocates</hi> of <hi>Liberti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſme</hi> now adaies, for a <hi>Toleration</hi> of all, how ever <hi>errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Schiſmaticall,</hi> or <hi>Blaſphemous,</hi> who <hi>pretend to Anointing:</hi> as if the very name of <hi>Saints</hi> were a ſufficient <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> an univerſall <hi>Protection</hi> to them from all <hi>Civill,</hi> or <hi>Church-cenſures)</hi> to whoſe pleas in behalfe of <hi>Anointed Saints</hi> (in caſe he will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe alſo out of that <hi>Charter of Liberty, who diſſolve the continuity of the Body by groundleſſe ſchiſme,</hi> and breaking the <hi>Laws</hi> that keepe it united; as he hath thoſe, who by <hi>fundamentall Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi> and <hi>damnable Hereſies, ſtrike at,</hi> or <hi>hold not the head,)</hi> I can readily give my vote, and approbation.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">The former branch limited.</note> But concerning thoſe of both ſorts, who now moſt engroſſe the name of <hi>Saints,</hi> as if they had gotten a <hi>Patent</hi> from the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> to that purpoſe; let them know, the Scripture never gives <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> a ſtricter charge concerning them, then it gives to <hi>Angels;</hi> and theſe (though they <hi>pitch their tents round about thoſe that feare God)</hi> have no other Orders given them
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112834:6"/> (that I reade of) then, to keepe them in all <hi>their waies.</hi> If they deſtroy foundations of Religion, and fight againſt its moſt materiall principles, nay if they ſtraggle from the <hi>Body,</hi> when they ſhould <hi>march cloſe</hi> in it; if when they ſhould fight <hi>united,</hi> they will <hi>divide</hi> themſelves into <hi>Parties</hi> without <hi>command;</hi> if they ſhall leape over the <hi>hedge of Order,</hi> and ride <hi>ſcouting</hi> after their owne ſingular <hi>humours,</hi> or <hi>plundering</hi> their brethren of the <hi>faith once delivered to the Saints;</hi> and ſo endanger, not <note place="margin">Deut. 2. &amp;c. 13. 5. 6. 9. 2 Chro. 15. 12, 13.</note> onely <hi>themſelves,</hi> but the <hi>body</hi> by their deſtructive doctrines, examples and practiſes; (and of this nature divers ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions more might bee added) ſure, the <hi>Civill Gods</hi> may <hi>touch</hi> them with a <hi>penalty,</hi> and the <hi>Church-Angels</hi> with a <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 5. 12. Apoc. 2. 13. 20.</note> 
               <hi>cenſure.</hi> And although the <hi>men</hi> may not be <hi>evill;</hi> yet <hi>Peter</hi> ſuppoſeth they may <hi>bee,</hi> and <hi>ſuffer,</hi> as <hi>evill-doers,</hi> as <hi>buſie-bodies,</hi> 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 4. 15.</p>
            <p>If they break the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>mans,</hi> (the ſubmiſſion unto which doth not contradict <hi>Gods) God,</hi> as he is not <hi>Author,</hi> ſo he will not be <hi>Patron</hi> of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> by exempting them from ſatisfying the <hi>Lawes</hi> they have broken. And as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Jewes</hi> concerning <hi>Circumciſion, Verily thy Circumciſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth thee, if thou be a keeper of the Law; but if thou be a breaker of the Law, thy Circumciſion is made uncircumciſion, Rom.</hi> 2. 25. So I to them concerning <hi>Saintſhip.</hi> Verily thy <hi>Saintſhip</hi> profits thee, if thou be <hi>obedient</hi> to juſt <hi>Lawes;</hi> but if not, now <hi>Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> muſt not be thy <hi>Sanctuary;</hi> (as to thy <hi>Priviledge)</hi> thy <hi>Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> is <hi>unſainted;</hi> and though (as <hi>Joab)</hi> thou fly to the hornes of that <hi>Altar,</hi> thou maiſt (without the <hi>Rebuke</hi> in the Text to thy <hi>Cenſurers)</hi> be taken from it, and be ſafely puniſhed.</p>
            <p>But I intend onely to <hi>touch</hi> at this <hi>Nolite tangere.</hi> The worke I have cut out for the ſubject of my Diſcourſe, and your atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the latter <hi>branch</hi> of the <hi>Charge,</hi> which concernes the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> as <hi>Prophets.</hi> And although that ſubject be leſſe <hi>popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Explication of the latter clauſe</note> and ſo leſſe <hi>toothſome,</hi> or <hi>plauſible,</hi> I hope my <hi>Text</hi> will bee my ſecurity.</p>
            <p>
               <q>And doe my Prophets no harme.</q>
               <q>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prophetas dicit non ſolum quia Deus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius ſe illis patefecerat, ſed quia coeleſtem Doctrinam fideliter propagarunt,</hi> Galv. ad locum.</note> [Doe my Prophets no harme] Prophetas dicit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> (ſaith reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112834:7"/> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place) He calls them <hi>Prophets,</hi> not onely for their nearer <hi>communion</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> but for their faithfull <hi>ſpreading</hi> the <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>God, [My]</hi> Prophets, that is, thoſe whom I have Commiſſioned to ſpeake in my name. And this <hi>Ratio nominis,</hi> ſuting with all alike <hi>commiſſioned</hi> to the worlds end, makes the charge not <hi>peculiar</hi> to <hi>Patriarchall,</hi> but <hi>common</hi> to <hi>Paſtorall</hi> Prophets, to the worlds end. And ſo the divine ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat here given to theſe Kings concerning theſe Prophets (as ſuch) hath to me the force of an univerſall caution to all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, concerning all Gods Prophets. Doe theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prophets of mine <hi>[no harm]</hi> that is, no <hi>injury.</hi> No exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this, (no not for Prophets) from the <hi>power</hi> of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, <note place="margin">The latter clauſe limited.</note> (if ſo, it would not ſtand with the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1.) but from <hi>unjuſt ſuffering</hi> by, or under that <hi>power.</hi> And ſure whereinſoever <hi>God</hi> will <hi>owne</hi> them for his <hi>Prophets, whatever</hi> they doe in <hi>diſcharge</hi> of their <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> in that God will <hi>owne</hi> their <hi>wrongs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall in the concluſion which I draw from theſe words, take <note place="margin">The Doctrine grounded.</note> my riſe from the Brothers <hi>ground,</hi> who hath diſpatcht the preceding part of the Text; who layes this ſuppoſition for me, that this Rebuke of <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Kings,</hi> holds forth the <hi>grand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Kings, &amp; Kingdomes.</hi> Now if it be true of the former <hi>branch,</hi> the <hi>connexion</hi> tells me it is ſo of the latter too. <hi>Que Deus conjunxit,</hi> &amp;c. What God hath joyned, I hope no man will divide. Nor ſhall I: And therefore whatſoever Intereſt the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> concernes; that the uſage of Prophets concernes it as nearly, I ſhall firſt <hi>propound,</hi> then <hi>prove,</hi> then <hi>improve</hi> in this Propoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Whatever bee the great and high Intereſts of Kings, States, and Kingdomes, on which their ſafety, or ruine moſt depends, there is none it concernes them more to look to, then the dealing well or ill with the Prophets of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proofe of this point, whatever the aforeſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <note place="margin">Proved,</note> hath <hi>gleaned</hi> to ſtrengthen his <hi>Intereſt,</hi> I might make uſe of to confirme this. 'Twill be an Argument that may perhaps <note place="margin">By compariſon with the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in reference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Saints.</note> conclude more then the Doctrine affirmes, that if the greateſt and moſt flouriſhing Kingdomes, have been <hi>broken</hi> by their ill <hi>uſing,</hi> or proſpered by their <hi>well-uſing</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> of God: If
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112834:7"/> God dealt with them, accordingly as they did with his <hi>Saints:</hi> much more may it be verified concerning the <hi>uſage</hi> of <hi>Prophets,</hi> where ſuch flouriſhing Kingdomes have had to doe with them. And if God be ſo tender of <hi>Saints,</hi> as <hi>Saints;</hi> ſure, hee will bee more tender of thoſe <hi>Saints</hi> that are <hi>Prophets</hi> too; ſeeing they have not only an <hi>holineſſe</hi> of <hi>Eſtate,</hi> but an <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> of <hi>Office,</hi> to endeare them to him: in that God lookes not on them onely as his <hi>Subjects,</hi> but takes care of them like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as his <hi>Ambaſſadors.</hi> Sure if the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> will reſolve on <hi>Peace</hi> or <hi>Warre</hi> with any Nation, according as they uſe any of his ordinary <hi>Subjects;</hi> hee will reſolve more effectually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the entertainment of his <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Ambaſſadours.</hi> So that whatſoever can be ſaid concerning <hi>Saints</hi> in this caſe, concludes with double ſtrength concerning <hi>Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I need not be beholden to <hi>Compariſon</hi> for the proofe of a <note n="1" place="margin">1. From Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> Truth ſo <hi>poſitively</hi> confirmed in the whole Scripture, there being nothing in which it ſpeaks more fully then it doth to this Point. I ſhall (though not enough read to fill my <hi>Boſome</hi> with ſuch <hi>Collections,</hi> yet) endeavour to fill my <hi>hand;</hi> and thoſe I ſhall make uſe of, ſhall be ſo cleare, and convincing that I hope I ſhall be able to affirme (without an overvaluing my weake labour in this kinde) that theſe <hi>gleanings of Ephraim</hi> are not <hi>beneath</hi> the <hi>vintage of Abiezer (i. e.)</hi> that I have proved as much (at leaſt) for the <hi>Intereſt of Kings</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes</hi> in reference to <hi>Prophets,</hi> as hath already been for that to <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place, will you have a <hi>word</hi> for this <hi>Intereſt?</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. 20. and <hi>Ier.</hi> 20. 11. (compared) will acquaint you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. <note place="margin">By poſitive expreſſions of Scripture to this effect.</note> In the former of theſe, you ſhall find King <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> encouraging, and directing his people, now ready to ioyne iſſue with a numerous Army; (and you will conceive that at ſuch a time, hee will minde them of that which moſt concernes them) And what is that? why? you have Prophets, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage you in Gods name, to confidence of ſucceſſe, ſee how you uſe them, beware you doe not diſtruſt them; <hi>Beleeve his Prophets, and yee ſhall proſper.</hi> In the laſt of theſe, you have <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> the <hi>Prophet</hi> complaining of hard uſage from his <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi> They raiſed lyes upon him and watched <hi>advantages</hi> to defame him, but what collects he from this? ſee v. 11. my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112834:8"/> 
               <hi>perſecutors ſhall be aſhamed (therefore i. e.</hi> becauſe they uſe a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> of God ſo) <hi>they ſhall not proſper.</hi> Thus then, the uſage of the prophets of God hath a great influence upon the <hi>proſpering,</hi> or <hi>not proſpering</hi> of a people. And ſure then, they have no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Intereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will you have the Teſtimony of a Prophet concerning a Prophet? <hi>Elijab</hi> being now to be mounted to heaven in a fiery chariot, <hi>Eliſha</hi> who ſaw how hee would be wanted, ſends this <hi>Teſtimony</hi> concerning him, in a <hi>Sigh</hi> after him. <hi>My father, My father, the Chariot of Iſrael, and the horſmen thereof.</hi> 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 2. 12. And if you will have a <hi>Kings</hi> concerning <hi>Eliſha himſelfe,</hi> you ſhall ſee <hi>Ioaſh</hi> giving the ſame Teſtimony of him <hi>ch.</hi> 13. 14.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Expreſſion</hi> implies it to bee the high <hi>engagement</hi> that lyes upon <hi>States</hi> and <hi>States-men,</hi> to looke to the keeping and protecting of their <hi>Prophets</hi> among them: There is nothing it more concernes <hi>Princes</hi> or people to looke to, then their <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary proviſions;</hi> (tis the ſecurity of a people) and theſe are <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. [Take &amp;c.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will you have <hi>examples?</hi> ſcriptures are thronged with them <note n="2" place="margin">2. By Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</note> in all the <hi>Hiſtoricall</hi> part. I ſhal inſtance firſt in <hi>Scripture Records of heathen Princes</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes;</hi> then I ſhall give you a briefe <hi>Epitome</hi> of the Scriptures <hi>eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory</hi> concerning it, and ſo conclude the confirmation by teſtimonies from the word.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Prophet</hi> I finde taken notice of for his uſage among <note place="margin">Of Heathen Kings, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, or both.</note> 
               <hi>Heathens</hi> is this <hi>Abraham.</hi> How God rebuked Kings for his ſake, the places I have already quoted wil abundantly ſhew. And leſt you ſhould ſay this care was taken of him only as of a common Saint; God himſelfe, when he declares how much <hi>Abimelech</hi> is concern'd in his uſage, tells him he is a <hi>prophet, and ſhall pray for him. Gen.</hi> 20. 7. As if he ſhould have ſaid, thou doſt not know whom thou now haſt in thy power. Didſt thou know what a <hi>Prophets prayers</hi> will doe with mee, thou wouldeſt reſtore this man his wife; thou would'ſt beware how thou uſed'ſt a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. And truly the cauſe of a King, yea of a Kingdom may be ſuch ſometimes, that the <hi>prayers of Prophets</hi> may have a great <hi>influence</hi> on the turning of it either way. Witneſſe <hi>Moſes</hi> his often ſtanding in the <hi>Gap:</hi> witneſſe Gods <hi>ſtopping Ieremiahs</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:112834:8"/> mouth, the <hi>laſt</hi> and ſaddeſt ſymptome of the peoples <hi>totall capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,</hi> Jer. 7. 16. 11. 14. And by the way; I ſhall conclude the State of that Prince, and his Kingdome <hi>deſperate,</hi> where I ſee the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of prayer <hi>bound</hi> up in its Prophets; and preſage a growing <hi>bappineſſe</hi> towards it, when I find them <hi>enlarged</hi> in <hi>mediating</hi> for it unto God. Sure, that State is <hi>blind</hi> to its Intereſt, that hath provoked God, by abuſing Prophets, to ſtrike his Prophets <hi>dumbe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to goe on. The next Prophet among <hi>Heathens</hi> was <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and hee was ſent to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to bring Iſrael out of Egypt. Now <hi>Pharaohs</hi> and <hi>Aegypts</hi> Intereſt was <hi>double;</hi> to uſe the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> well, and ſet the <hi>people</hi> free. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> now croſſeth both theſe Intereſts; <hi>detaines</hi> the people, and <hi>abuſeth</hi> Moſes. Now if we may <hi>balance</hi> theſe Intereſts, it may ſeem his uſage of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet did moſt <hi>concern</hi> him. For although after many plagues, God were pleaſed to deſtroy the firſt borne, &amp; overthrow him and his Hoſt in the red Sea, to ſet his people free; yet he never writes his <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> in ſuch <hi>bloody characters,</hi> till the wretched King had driven <hi>Moſes</hi> from his ſight, and commanded him <hi>to ſee his face no more,</hi> and threatned him death if he did, <hi>Exod.</hi> 10. 28. compared with the ſequell.</p>
            <p>Come we a little lower. <hi>Jonah</hi> is ſent by God with a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of deſtruction to <hi>Niniveh,</hi> and the utmoſt reſpite hee was to give them was but <hi>forty dayes.</hi> One would have expected ſuch an unwelcome meſſenger as he, ſhould have rather found his <hi>death from</hi> them, then <hi>acceptance among</hi> them. But the wiſe King knew (though an Heathen) what concern'd him to doe. And to worke he goes. He entertaines the Prophet, and his meſſage ſo well, that he commands a ſolemn Humiliation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall ſaves his City, which no other way could have reſcued from ruine. That was the great <hi>Intereſt</hi> of that City, and that well looked too, kept out the deſtroyers.</p>
            <p>[Take one word 200 concerning the <hi>New-Teſtament Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and of how great concernment the uſage of them was to thoſe places where they came, let the great <hi>Goſpell Prophet</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe teſtifie. It concernes them <hi>(ſaith he that was annoynted with the oyle of gladneſſe above his fellows)</hi> as nearly, as it concerns them to well entreate God the Father, and my ſelfe. For (ſaith he)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112834:9"/> 
               <hi>Whoever deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me, and whoever deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me.</hi> Sure then the uſage of Gods Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers is as great a point of State-Intereſt as any can be, to all, except thoſe that think themſelves then leaſt <hi>loſers,</hi> when they have <hi>loſt</hi> their <hi>God.</hi>]</p>
            <p>I ſhall give you only one example out of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> upon this Head. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt ſent by God to <hi>prepare the way</hi> for Chriſt among the Jewes, begins to grow much in requeſt with <hi>Herod,</hi> an Heathen Subſtitute, appointed by the Romans to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern them. <hi>Herod</hi> carries himſelfe fairely a while towards <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, heares him gladly, and doth many things. And yet with thoſe many good things, he had many evill too: Many filthy vices he was guilty of, but the holy Ghoſt takes notice of this <hi>above all the reſt; That he put</hi> John <hi>in priſon.</hi> The Text fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tells us how his freeneſſe to the King in medling with his <hi>Herodias,</hi> rob'd him not only of his liberty, but his life. And a ſecond reaſon why <hi>Herod</hi> ſlew him, <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſaith, was for feare of the people, becauſe they were ready to entertaine any new motion from one whoſe word had ſo great a ſway with them <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </note>. And ſee how deare it coſt him; the ſame <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſaies, the Jewes lookt upon the victory that <hi>Aretas</hi> gained over him, and his Army, as cauſed thereby <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Lib. Iud. Ant.</hi> 18. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note>. And how God met with him too in his Perſon, &amp; with that <hi>Herodias</hi> that wooed him to ſo bloody an action, will appeare if wee conſider what the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the Centuries relate out of both <hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Euſebius.</hi> That <hi>whoriſh</hi> woman (how proper is the Scripture conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe two qualities! <note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 16. 30.</note>) was no leſſe imperious; and out of her deſire to command, envying <hi>Agrippa</hi> (her owne Brother) the honour of being a King, while her inceſtuous husband ſate a ſtaire lower, tempts him to a journy to <hi>Rome,</hi> to <hi>beg a Crown,</hi> and to compaſſe it more effectually, attends him thither. When he came thither, he found his plot ſpoiled by a prepared <hi>jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> againſt him; and his ambitious preparations for Royalty, proved the <hi>inditement,</hi> and a ſentence to perpetuall exile, was the <hi>judgement</hi> paſt againſt him by the Emperour. In which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe had brought him to it) this Tempter was ſo kinde as to accompany him. <hi>And ſo</hi> (ſay the Centuriaſts) Herod <hi>by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with the motions of an ambitious Whore, ſtript of his goods,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:112834:9"/> 
               <hi>Countrey, glory at once, dyed miſerably with her in Gallia</hi> (<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hac ratione arrogantis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retriculae inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationibus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperans He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodes, cum ipſâ bonis, gloria ac patriâ exutus miſerrimè in Gallia vitam finiit. Cent. Magd. Cent.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note>). Thus he that was <hi>afraid of</hi> John, <hi>and kill'd him out of a jealouſie to ſecure his Command,</hi> thereby provoked God by a <hi>jealouſie to out him of his Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us in the next place, <note n="d" place="margin">2. Examples of thoſe within the Church.</note> take a view of the uſage of <hi>Prophets within</hi> the Church. And in this you ſhall ſee how thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or Kingdoms, have thrived, that have offended againſt this <hi>Intereſt.</hi> I ſhall (for <hi>methods</hi> ſake) branch this view into <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars;</hi> in which you ſhall alſo ſee, when God thinkes his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets injured; by his ſuiting ſuch dealings of men towards them, with ſuitable <note n="e" place="margin">Shewing the iſſue of croſſing this Intereſt in harming Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</note> diſpenſations of juſtice, upon the heads of thoſe that ſo deal with them: and ſo I ſhall ſave the anſwering of that queſtion, what it is to harm Prophets.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How they have <note n="f" place="margin">1. Perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing only to hear them.</note> ſped that have harmed Prophets only by refuſing to heare them; let <hi>Zach.</hi> 7. 9, 10, 11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be firſt called in to give <hi>Evidence.</hi> The Lord had <hi>ſent</hi> to them (as himſelfe ſaith) <hi>in his Spirit, by his Prophets, but they refuſed to hearken, &amp; pulled away the ſhoulder;</hi> (it ſeems 'twas doctrine they were loath to <hi>beare) and ſtopped their eares.</hi> Nay, they reſolv'd againſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to any purpoſe, if they did heare; for they had before (by a wicked reſolution of rejecting what they thought would not tickle them) made <hi>their hearts</hi> like <hi>an Adamant,</hi> that is, <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-proofe,</hi> and <hi>conviction-proofe,</hi> leſt they ſhould heare the <hi>Law.</hi> The Prophets were <hi>legall Preachers,</hi> and they would hear none of them; at leaſt armed themſelves with <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>prejudice,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to render their labours ineffectuall upon them. But what great matter was this? Was it a buſineſſe of ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to them to heare, or not to heare, ſuch men as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them no better? Yes, they had better they had heard them, for God paid them in their own coyne. Well (ſaith hee) they would not heare my Prophets, but I think I met with them; I remember there was a time when they <hi>called upon me</hi> to heare, &amp; I was grown as deaf as they; <hi>They cryed, and I would not heare,</hi> verſ. 13. <hi>I ſcattered them with a Whirl-wind among the Nations which they knew not, &amp;c.</hi> verſ. 14. I ſent them where they had been as good to have been among <hi>deafe</hi> people as there, for they <hi>knew them not, and the land was deſolate after them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One teſtimony more to this particular. That which is in this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112834:10"/> Chapter <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> is <hi>(Jer.</hi> 25. 3, 4.) <hi>Propheſie. The Lord</hi> ſaith he to this people, <hi>hath ſent unto you all his Prophets, riſing early, and ſending them, but yee hearkned not, nor enclined your eare.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you have part of that doom threatned, which you had in that of <hi>Zachariah,</hi> related.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Preſcribers to Prophets.</hi> See to this purpoſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 10. <note n="2" place="margin">2. Preſcribing to Prophets.</note> The Lord makes a ſad complaint of that people; they were a <hi>rebellious people,</hi> verſ. 9. But how doth it appear? <hi>They ſay to the Seers, ſee not; and to the Prophets, propheſie not unto us right things, ſpeake to us ſmooth things, propheſie deceits? Get yee out of the way, turne yee out of the path, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis very unlikely they would dare ſay ſo in down-right terms. No, it may be they ſaid no more but, <hi>pray</hi> Iſaiah, <hi>and the reſt of the Prophets doe not preach to us that which croſſeth us in our way; cannot you be contented to preach practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call truths to us, and not trouble your ſelves with State-buſineſſes? what doth it concerne you, if we goe down to Aegypt for ſecurity and aſſiſtance?</hi> But you ſee how God interprets them, 'tis ſaith hee, <hi>a bidding the Seers not to ſee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what great matter is this? What matter of moment or concernment in giving the Prophets a <hi>preparatory leſſon</hi> of our owne? We hope all this is no <hi>harme</hi> to the Prophets, nor <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> to us. See whether God thinke ſo too, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13, 14. Indeed? (ſaith God) are you <hi>ſwoln</hi> ſo great with <hi>pride,</hi> that you muſt give <hi>Inſtructions</hi> to my <hi>Ambaſſadours?</hi> yea, and you ſhall <hi>ſwell bigger</hi> yet, and that till you <hi>breake</hi> into <hi>minutula fruſtula;</hi> ſuch <hi>ſherds</hi> as are uſefull for nothing, <hi>no not to take fire from the hearth, or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Pit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Deriders of Prophets,</hi> 2 Chron. 36. 16. This it ſeemes that <note n="3" place="margin">3. Deriding Prophets.</note> people were very well verſed in. But what is all that! if a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple make themſelves <hi>merry,</hi> and pleaſe themſelves a little with <hi>jeſting</hi> at <hi>Prophets?</hi> Indeed <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us 'tis a <hi>ſport to a foole to do miſchiefe, and there is a mad man that throwes about fire-brands,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 10. 23. 26. 29.</note> 
               <hi>arrowes, and death; and yet cries, Am I not in ſport?</hi> But theſe mad men think not they <hi>jeere</hi> and <hi>ſport</hi> themſelves out of their <hi>hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>eſtates</hi> by this <hi>mirth.</hi> Yet they doe ſo. For though <hi>they</hi> be in <hi>jeſt,</hi> God is in <hi>earneſt</hi> with them. They never left ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing at Prophets till they had brought wrath <hi>(viz.)</hi> in the Captivity, upon themſelves <hi>without remedie,</hi> ſaith the ſequell of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112834:10"/> the verſe. 'Tis a deare jeſting that coſts a Kingdom all its mirth for ever after.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Permitters,</hi> or <hi>encouragers</hi> of <hi>falſe Prophets.</hi> The great <hi>Patron</hi> 
               <note n="4" place="margin">4. Permitting or encouraging falſe Prophets.</note> of falſe Prophets in ſcripture, was <hi>Ahab.</hi> A poore Prophet of the Lord could not <hi>looke abroad,</hi> but hee was charged, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted as a <hi>troubler</hi> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The falſe Prophets <hi>ſwarmed,</hi> no leſſe then 450, Ahabs, 400, <hi>Iezebels</hi> Chaplaines. 1. <hi>K.</hi> 18. 19. And when the King conſults concerning war with Ramoth-Gilead, one <hi>Micaiah</hi> could not be heard, becauſe hee did not <hi>pleaſe</hi> his Majeſty: but the falſe prophets were his great Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. But how God fitted him, and his Army, 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 22. will fully declare. But I will ſpeake more to it anon.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> much inſiſts upon this particular. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. Hee tells us of ſome of them of whom God himſelfe, v. 12. witneſſeth <hi>they ſpake lies in his name;</hi> but what becomes of them? <hi>by ſword, and famine they ſhall be conſumed.</hi> v. 13. But what doth this concerne the Kingdome, or Nation? ſee. v. 16. And the people to <hi>whom they propheſy, ſhall be caſt out in the ſtreets of Ieruſalem, becauſe of the famine, and the ſword &amp;c. for I will powr their wickedneſſe upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. (almoſt throughout) God complaines of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that ſent <hi>themſelves,</hi> and yet they would <hi>ape</hi> the true Prophets, and cry the <hi>Burthen of the Lord &amp;c.</hi> and this was grown Epidemicall, v. 34. <hi>Prieſts, and people, and Prophets exerciſe</hi> their <hi>gifts</hi> promiſcuouſly; ſee how God takes this at their hands, and the Toleration of it at the States: Not onely they, but the City are threatned ruine for it. v. 39. All rankes of men were out of the order in which God had placed them; they had turned Gods inſtitutions up and downe, and God would turne <hi>them</hi> up and downe for it. God takes it as an high affront, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they did themſelves, or ſuffered others, to wrong his Husbandmen ſo far, as to lay <hi>Common</hi> what hee himſelfe had <hi>incloſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Threatners of Prophets</hi> 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 25. 15. <hi>Amaziah</hi> a wicked <note n="5" place="margin">5. Threatning Prophets.</note> King had <hi>gained</hi> a <hi>victory</hi> over the Edomites, to the loſſe of his <hi>Religion.</hi> Hee tooke the <hi>enemies captive,</hi> and yeilded himſelfe <hi>Captive</hi> to their <hi>Idols.</hi> God ſends a Prophet to him, and pleads the caſe with him, ſhewes him how unreaſonable tis to expect
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112834:11"/> ſafety from thoſe Gods that were now his <hi>Priſoners.</hi> And how doth he entertain the Prophet? with a check, <hi>[Art thou of the Kings Counſell]</hi> and a threat; <hi>[Forbeare, why ſhouldſt thou be ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten?]</hi> Here was no harme yet; but a threatning onely; and is that ſo much?</p>
            <p>But how doth God take it? ſee in the Prophets reply, and the ſequell of the ſtory. The Prophet ſeeing him ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of his great Intereſt, askes no farther evidence, or <hi>Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtick</hi> of his ſuddain <hi>ruine,</hi> and therefore is bold to tell him, <hi>I know that God hath purpoſed</hi> [Orig. <hi>counſelled</hi>] <hi>to deſtroy thee, becauſe thou haſt not harkned to my counſell.</hi> And a little after, the fooliſh man ſtirres the coales that ſet him and his Kingdome on fire, in provoking <hi>Joaſh</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael, v.</hi> 15, 16, 17, 22, 23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He had better to have <hi>taken Counſell from God</hi> by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, then have provoked God <hi>to take Counſell againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Silencers of Prophets, Amos</hi> 7. It was in the dayes of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi> 
               <note n="6" place="margin">6. Silencing Prophets.</note> the ſonne of <hi>Joaſh</hi> (a wicked King, as you may ſee 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 14. 24.) when this Prophet propheſied. The matter of his Propheſie was the captivity of <hi>Iſrael: Amaziah,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Bethel</hi> takes him up for it, and accuſeth him highly for ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unto the King, <hi>v.</hi> 10. 12. And (very likely by the command of the King) forbids him to preach any more in <hi>Bethel.</hi> This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is an uſage ſomething to the purpoſe. God ſaith, <hi>Speak;</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maziah ſaith, <hi>Speak not.</hi> And what ſaith God now to <hi>Amaziah?</hi> ſee his doom, v. 17. <hi>Thy wife ſhal be an harlot in the City, &amp; thy ſons, and thy daughters ſhall fall by the ſword, &amp;c.</hi> And what is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome concerned in it? their ſhare is no leſſe then to be <hi>captives forth of their land.</hi> Thou, ſaith <hi>Amos,</hi> bidſt me goe forth of the Court, and propheſie: if I goe forth to propheſie, and muſt not propheſie here, God ſhall <hi>ſend</hi> more after me: <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall go <hi>forth too</hi> out of their Land. And not many years after in <hi>Pekah's</hi> time, (the throne having ſcarce been warmed by any King of four, except <hi>Menahem)</hi> this Propheſie was in part fulfilled, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 15. 29. and perfectly in his ſucceſſour, <hi>Hoſheas</hi> time, <hi>chap.</hi> 16. 6. 18, &amp;c. And as for <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> although the Hiſtory doe not tell us how he dyed, yet the Propheſie doth, in that <hi>Amos</hi> 7. and his ſeed were diſpoſſeſſed of the Throne; onely <hi>Zechariah,</hi> (becauſe the fourth from <hi>Jehu;</hi> to whoſe ſeed God had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112834:11"/> a ſucceſſion for foure generations, as it appeares Chapt. 10. 30. and 15. 12.) was permitted to hold the Scepter ſix moneths, as appeares, <hi>verſe</hi> 8. <hi>chap.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>Next, that you may ſee 'twas not onely <hi>Amaziah's</hi> uſage of <hi>Amos,</hi> that brought, (though it haſtned) the peoples Captivity: You ſhall ſee this judgement is threatned for the olde <hi>skore too.—Manet altâ mente repoſtum.</hi> God forgets not how they uſed his Prophets in all ages, even from the dayes of <hi>Egypt:</hi> and now they ſhall pay for it <hi>with a witneſse, Chapter</hi> 2. 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. <hi>I raiſed up of your ſonnes for Prophets, and of your young men for Nazarites,</hi> verſe 11. <hi>Yee commanded the Prophets, Propheſie not,</hi> verſe 12. <hi>Behold I am preſſed with you, &amp;c.</hi> 13. How God feeles Prophets wrongs! <hi>Therefore the flight ſhall periſh from the ſwift, and the ſtrong ſhall not ſtrengthen himſelfe, nor the mighty deliver himſelfe,</hi> verſe 14. <hi>nor Bow-man, nor rider,</hi> verſe 15. <hi>nor the ſtrong of heart,</hi> verſe 16. This likewiſe was fulfilled in the captivity of the Tribes before mentioned.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Impriſoners of Prophets.</hi> And now I muſt look back once <note n="7" place="margin">7. Impriſoning Prophets.</note> more upon <hi>Ahab.</hi> It was not enough for that <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>wretched King</hi> to <hi>encourage and maintaine</hi> falſe Prophets to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front <hi>Micaiah;</hi> to <hi>refuſe to heare him</hi> out of prejudice: but when good <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> had prevailed to have him adviſed with, and he had declared the minde of God to him, he <hi>ſuffers a falſe Prophet to ſmite him, and claps him up for his plain dealing,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. 27. Now what became of this <hi>Ahab?</hi> God meets with him at laſt; <hi>Micaiah</hi> tells him, if <hi>he came home in peace, God had not ſpoken by him,</hi> verſe 28. No! (thinks <hi>Ahab)</hi> I will try that once; I will ſee if I cannot prove this Prophet a lyer. He ſhifts his habit, <hi>changeth cloathes</hi> with <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> and thereby diverts the greateſt force of the battell upon <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> miſtaken for the King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But <hi>Ahab</hi> is not <hi>ſafe,</hi> though he be <hi>ſecure</hi> in his <hi>diſguiſe,</hi> and <hi>Armour</hi> upon that. A certaine man muſt <hi>draw a Bow at a venture,</hi> and <hi>ſhoot,</hi> and the <hi>Arrow</hi> muſt light on none of all the Army but <hi>Ahab,</hi> and on no other place about <hi>Ahab's</hi> body, but directly between the <hi>joynts of his Armour,</hi> verſe 34. and the wound muſt be mortall too: and thus for <hi>impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning</hi> his Prophet God brought him to <hi>execution;</hi> and his <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> after a long conflict were faine to retreat, <hi>verſe</hi> 36. Once
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112834:12"/> more. The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> tells us, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. 16. that the Jewes did not onely <hi>mock,</hi> but <hi>miſuſe</hi> the Prophets of God, till they brought upon them a remedileſſe captivity. Now among all the Prophets uſages that haſtned this calamity, it is more then probable, that the <hi>impriſoning Jeremiah</hi> by the Princes did <hi>poſte</hi> it forward; and God ('tis likely enough) <hi>gave up</hi> the <hi>City</hi> to <hi>deliver a Prophet:</hi> for when the <hi>ſtore of bread was ſpent in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> likely to ſtarve, (as <hi>Jerem.</hi> 38. 9.) the City holds not out long after, and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> is preſerved by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring Enemy, <hi>chap.</hi> 39. 11.</p>
            <p>8. <hi>Laſtly, Murderers of Prophets.</hi> This was a ſinne ordinary <note n="8" place="margin">8. Murthering Prophets.</note> with the Jewes; and for this Chriſt bemoanes them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 37. <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou that killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them that are ſent unto thee, how often would I have gathered together thy children as an henne, &amp;c.</hi> (that is, I by my Prophets, and by my ſelfe would, if thou hadſt <hi>knowne</hi> thy <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>taken</hi> that <hi>Protection</hi> by receiving, and obeying us) but thou (fooliſh people) art an <hi>enemy,</hi> and ever haſt beene, to thy <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> in this great particular; 'tis that, at which thy <hi>hand</hi> is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily <hi>in,</hi> to <hi>kill</hi> Prophets. And this he makes good in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, where propheſying of his owne death, he tells his Diſciples, that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is ſo <hi>fleſhed with killing Prophets,</hi> that a <hi>Prophet cannot periſh out of Jeruſalem,</hi> Luke 13. 33. But the cry of <hi>bloud is loud;</hi> and the <hi>cry of Prophets bloud,</hi> of all other, <hi>moſt clamorous.</hi> Chriſt therefore <hi>preſageth</hi> ſo <hi>certaine</hi> a ruine to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for killing Gods Meſſengers, that he <hi>pronounceth</hi> it as <hi>paſt. Verily your houſe [is] left unto you deſolate.</hi> This ſinne you are ſo given to, (when by <hi>killing</hi> mee, and perſecuting my Apoſtles, you ſhall have <hi>filled</hi> up the <hi>meaſure of the ſinnes</hi> of your Prophet-murthering Anceſtors, and your owne) ſhall bring the <hi>Romans</hi> to your houſes, and they ſhall leave <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> a company of deſolate Walls in it, ſhall make a wildernes (ſo the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> word ſignifies) of your houſes, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> either of your particular habitations, or your <hi>glorious Temple;</hi> of which (as he elſewhere ſaith) <hi>There ſhall not one ſtone bee left upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How theſe <hi>Jewes</hi> haſtned this deſtruction to themſelves by putting to death <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, &amp; perſecuting his Apoſtles, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112834:12"/> Sermon I have already quoted makes good abundantly. I ſhall take no more notice of it here, then to obſerve, that (as God prophecying concerning their oppoſing <hi>Chriſt, Pſ.</hi> 2. takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice mainly of their ſpight againſt him as <hi>Gods Annointed,</hi> ſo) he was mainly oppoſed under his Offices of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction;</hi> as a <hi>King,</hi> by <hi>Herod,</hi> as a <hi>Prophet,</hi> by high-Prieſts, Scribes, and Phariſees: who mainly conſult to ruine him, becauſe they ſaw him ſo follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as <hi>John</hi> 12. 19. (which ſeemes to me to be the ground of that conſultation related againe which they took, <hi>chap.</hi> 11. 47.) upon which <hi>verſe</hi> 53. they are ſaid to plot his death.</p>
            <p>And as for the Apoſtles, the maine ground of their ſpleene to them, (which was murther too in their intentions, and Gods account) was, <hi>their teaching in his Name,</hi> as they confeſſe <hi>Acts</hi> 4. ſo that Chriſt and his Apoſtles had their ſhare in the Jewes malice, and perſecution, <hi>as Prophets,</hi> as well <hi>as Saints;</hi> and how this bloud of former Prophets, and theſe did ſticke upon the skirts of that Nation, and how God tooke it, and what became of that bloudy people, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul propheſieth,</hi> and <hi>Ecleſiaſticall</hi> ſtories <hi>relate.</hi> The former tells us not onely the <hi>thing,</hi> but brings this as the <hi>cauſe</hi> to put all out of doubt, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 15, 16. where ſpeaking of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> he tells us, that they, in <hi>killing the Lord Jeſus, murthering their owne Prophets, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting him, and his fellow-Apoſtles, and forbidding them to preach to the Gentiles, filled up their ſinnes.</hi> (It referres to the afore-cited ſpeech of Chriſt, where he bids them <hi>fill up the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their Fathers, viz.</hi> thoſe that killed Prophets, by cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying him, and thus perſecuting his Apoſtles.) <hi>And wrath was come upon them to the utmoſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>[to the end] i. e.</hi> a <hi>finall wrath,</hi> a wrath that ſhould <hi>ſweep the Nation quite away,</hi> and make a <hi>cleane riddance</hi> of them. And as Chriſt prophecying of that deſtruction of the Jewes by the <hi>Romans</hi> ſpeaks of it as paſt, for greater <hi>certainty:</hi> ſo 'tis remarkable the Apoſtle doth. And whether theſe Propheſies were true or no, Hiſtory tells us abundantly, to which (for brevities ſake) I referre you.</p>
            <p>Now to draw all this proofe to an head, in one grand Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme, thus.</p>
            <p>That which being well looked unto, will advance the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, bee the Chariots and Horſe-men, keep out the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112834:13"/> of Princes and People; and which croſſed or neglected unſeats great ones, makes God conſult to deſtroy them, brings a ſword upon them, puts God upon the expence of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Providences, to ruine them, will hinder the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a people, makes them deſpiſers of God and Chriſt, ſtops Gods eares to them when they pray, ſcatters them with a Whirle-winde, breaks them into ſmalleſt, and moſt uſeleſſe ſheards, brings remedileſſe wrath upon them, ſends them out of their land, takes off the flight from the ſwift, ſtrength from the ſtrong, deliverance from the mighty, makes their houſes deſolate, fills up their ſinnes, and brings wrath upon them to the utmoſt; that is the great <hi>Intereſt</hi> of Princes and Kingdoms, then which they have no greater.</p>
            <p>But the uſage of the Prophets of God well or ill is influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall upon Kings and Kingdomes in all theſe particulars. <hi>Ergo,</hi> 'tis as great an <hi>Intereſt</hi> as any unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> 1. Out of many <hi>Reaſ.</hi> which might be brought, I ſhal bring <note place="margin">2 Proofe by Reaſons. 1. From Gods Intereſt in the Prophets.</note> onely three. 1. The firſt relates unto <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, and ſo is drawne from <hi>Gods Intereſt</hi> in the <hi>Prophets.</hi> And herein indeed, is the maine <hi>Emphaſis</hi> of the charge in the Text, <hi>Doe [my] Prophets no harme.</hi> I have already ſhewed you wherein Gods In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Prophets appeares to be greater then in ſingle Saints, I ſhall here onely make uſe of that truth againe as <hi>Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative</hi> to prove the Intereſt of which the Doctrine ſpeaks. Let us ſuppoſe a mighty Monarch, that hath <hi>millions</hi> of armed men to command at an <hi>hour's warning,</hi> to <hi>revenge</hi> any injury, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front done to him; ſending <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> to ſome <hi>petty Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality,</hi> his next neighbours, (not onely <hi>profeſſed enemies</hi> to him, but <hi>Rebells</hi> againſt him) and entreating them to lay down <hi>Armes,</hi> to be <hi>ruled</hi> by his <hi>Lawes,</hi> and <hi>enjoy</hi> the <hi>priviledges</hi> of <hi>his Subjects;</hi> eſpecially when it lyes in his <hi>power</hi> to take <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> and cut off, not onely their <hi>Proviſions</hi> for <hi>Warre;</hi> but their <hi>lives</hi> alſo every moment. What now would you conclude to be that poore <hi>handfulls</hi> maine Intereſt? Would it not bee, to <hi>entertaine</hi> thoſe <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> courteouſly, receive their Meſſage readily? and would they not offend againſt their maine Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, if they ſhould deny thoſe Ambaſſadors <hi>Audience;</hi> if they ſhould <hi>preſcribe</hi> to them what to ſay; if they ſhould <hi>deride</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:112834:13"/> them, and ſuffer every <hi>factious, anarchicall tumultuous</hi> ſpirit to <hi>write,</hi> and <hi>print,</hi> and <hi>preach</hi> Libells, and invectives againſt them, if they ſhould allow ſome of their owne, (that doe not <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand</hi> ſo much as the <hi>language</hi> in which that <hi>Kings Articles</hi> for <hi>Accommodation</hi> and <hi>Inſtructions</hi> for his <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) to ſtand up and tell thoſe Ambaſſadours, they know their Maſters minde better then they, that they <hi>teach</hi> the people <hi>lyes,</hi> &amp;c. If they hereupon ſhould <hi>threaten, ſilence, impriſon, put to death</hi> theſe <hi>Ambaſſadours,</hi> would they not provoke this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch to <hi>pluck</hi> them up, <hi>root</hi> and <hi>branch,</hi> to leave their <hi>houſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate,</hi> and fill them with wrath and vengeance to the <hi>uttermoſt?</hi> I need not apply ſo plaine a <hi>Parable.</hi> Look into <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 33, &amp;c. and 22, 23, &amp;c. and (change onely the meſſage of <hi>Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to the <hi>wedding</hi> in this, and that for <hi>fruit</hi> from the <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi> in that place into this concerning which I ſpeake a <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>Peace)</hi> what <hi>Chriſt intends</hi> in them to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> may be properly applyed to all Nations of <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to the end of the world, and may <hi>warn</hi> them to beware how they <hi>ſlight</hi> Gods Ambaſſadours; and looke upon Oxen, and Farmes, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, <hi>private</hi> Intereſts, when God calls upon them for <hi>acknowledgements</hi> to his <hi>Sonne;</hi> how they think the <hi>cruſhing</hi> and <hi>taking</hi> Gods <hi>Meſſengers out of the way,</hi> will make them the <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni fac-totum,</hi> the <hi>abſolute</hi> Maſters of Gods <hi>Inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>In regard of the Intereſt thoſe Prophets have in God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi> 
               <note n="2" place="margin">2. From the Prophets Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in God.</note> They have his <hi>engagement</hi> upon his <hi>honour,</hi> that he will take their <hi>wrongs</hi> as his <hi>owne,</hi> that he will interpret <hi>deſpiſing them</hi> to be <hi>deſpiſing him;</hi> that he will <hi>confirme the word of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and performe the counſell of his Meſſengers, Iſa.</hi> 44. 26. that he hath <hi>ſolemnly bound</hi> himſelfe to <hi>binde</hi> that in <hi>heaven by his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 18. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Ratification,</hi> which they (take it either for a binding of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> or of <hi>Cenſure,</hi> ſeeing theſe <hi>Scepticall dayes</hi> will needs qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the <hi>union</hi> of both <hi>keyes</hi> in the <hi>ſame hand)</hi> ſhal <hi>binde</hi> on <hi>earth</hi> by their <hi>Declaration</hi> according to their <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from him.</p>
            <p>Thence alſo, what God <hi>threatens</hi> a people <hi>to doe</hi> by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, they are ſaid to doe, as <hi>Jer.</hi> 1. 10. where God ſets his <hi>Prophet over kingdomes to root out, and pull downe, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtroy, and throw downe, and build, and plant,</hi> i. e. <hi>to pronounce</hi> that doome againſt a people, which he intended to <hi>bring</hi> upon them.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:112834:14"/>
            <p> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells us of a <hi>power,</hi> which he had <hi>not onely to throw downe imaginations, and every high thing that exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it ſelfe againſt the Knowledge of God, (viz.)</hi> that of his <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching:</hi> But a <hi>power,</hi> which he had alſo in <hi>readineſſe to revenge all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 6.</note> 
               <hi>diſobedience.</hi> Which <hi>power,</hi> if it be not a <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Church-cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> derived from <hi>Matthew</hi> 8. 18. (as ſome of the beſt Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters expound it) muſt needs bee a power of engaging <hi>GODS wrath</hi> againſt, and to the ruine of ſuch diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ones. And truely, by the way, the cryes of perſecuted Prophets are <hi>loud ones;</hi> for my part, I ſhould be loath any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or State, to which I wiſh well, ſhould <hi>force</hi> Gods Prophets to goe to him, and <hi>complaine</hi> of their <hi>uſage,</hi> and put him to it upon his engagement to right them; and (as the Scripture ſaith <hi>Elijah</hi> did) make Interceſſion <hi>againſt them.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> 3. The third Reaſon is drawne from the People them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <note n="3" place="margin">3. From the Intereſts which people and Prophets have reſpectively each in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> and the <hi>relation Prophets beare to them.</hi> The People are the <hi>ſheep,</hi> the Prophets are their <hi>ſhepheards,</hi> their <hi>Paſtours:</hi> Sure the <hi>Flocke</hi> is as highly concerned in <hi>having,</hi> and <hi>keeping</hi> a faithfull <hi>Shepheard</hi> as in any thing that can be imagined.</p>
            <p>They are their <hi>Watchmen.</hi> A people have no greater inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the time of <hi>war,</hi> or <hi>danger,</hi> then to look to their <hi>Guards,</hi> and encourage their <hi>Watchmen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are their <hi>lights, burning and ſhining lights.</hi> In a <hi>dark night,</hi> in a <hi>dangerous way,</hi> what concernes a <hi>Traveller</hi> more then to <hi>look</hi> to his <hi>light,</hi> to <hi>keep it in,</hi> and <hi>preſerve it cleare?</hi> They a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e their <hi>Salt,</hi> and there are <hi>putrifying</hi> dayes, <hi>corrupting</hi> times: Seducers, <hi>Children</hi> that <hi>are corrupters,</hi> like <hi>Fleſh-flies,</hi> ſwarme every where in the <hi>hot ſeaſon</hi> of <hi>Contention,</hi> and endeavour to <hi>taint</hi> the <hi>ſweeteſt natures, moſt tender hearts,</hi> and <hi>moſt pretious Spirits.</hi> Sure, 'tis the Magiſtrates (the good <hi>Houſe-keepers)</hi> ſpeciall Intereſt to get as much of this <hi>Salt</hi> as may be, to <hi>preſerve</hi> them from <hi>tainting;</hi> and to <hi>keep</hi> this <hi>Salt charily</hi> when they have it. There are divers other names of <hi>Relation</hi> in Scriptures that import as much, as <hi>Fathers, Stewards, Guides, &amp;c.</hi> But I think the Point a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly proved; To <hi>improve</hi> it to you in Application is my next worke.</p>
            <p>And in this I ſhall addreſſe my ſelfe to all thoſe that would
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112834:14"/> purſue Englands great Intereſt ſincerely, beſeeching them that <note place="margin">Applyed by</note> they will look to this, one of the greateſt <hi>branches,</hi> and of the <note place="margin">Exhortation to all to looke to this Intereſt. Among ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Intereſts purſued.</note> 
               <hi>top-boughes</hi> of it, the uſage of Gods Prophets among them.</p>
            <p>Beloved, there are many Intereſts this day <hi>ſtarted</hi> and <hi>purſued</hi> with a great deale of earneſtneſſe, &amp; it were well for the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of theſe Kingdomes, if ſome of them had been as the <hi>untimely birth of a woman that never ſees the Sun;</hi> at leaſt that they had never been taken up to thoſe uſes to which the <hi>Sons of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> now <hi>imploy</hi> them.</p>
            <p>By the way, whoſoever he was <hi>ſince our mutuall Covenant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Some deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, becauſe dividing.</note> firſt named an <hi>Engliſh Intereſt,</hi> in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to that of our <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Nation,</hi> it had been happy for both Nations in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>if the knees had not prevented him,</hi> and <hi>the breaſts had never given him ſuck;</hi> and truly (for my part,) I have ſo much <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-zeale</hi> yet <hi>glowing</hi> in my <hi>breaſt,</hi> that did I know him, I ſhould think my ſelf bound to <hi>diſcover, &amp; bring him to condigne puniſhment, as an Incendiary, Malignant, and evill Inſtrument, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to divide one Kingdome from another, contrary to the ſolemn League and Covenant.</hi> But among all theſe Intereſts, let me ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you to look to this <hi>piece</hi> of the <hi>higheſt</hi> Intereſt of all King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and all theſe Kingdomes, which I have all this while inſiſted upon.</p>
            <p>Beloved it is a ſubject that a man would have thought for <note place="margin">Need to preſs this Intereſt.</note> ſome yeares ſince he ſhould never have lived to ſee <hi>need</hi> to preſs. But we are unexpectedly caſt into ſuch times, in which we had need <hi>contend earneſtly</hi> for every <hi>title of the ancient Goſpell,</hi> and when <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſuffers the <hi>Diſpenſers</hi> of <hi>Chriſts</hi> truth cannot expect to be <hi>exempted.</hi> How ſhall thoſe men <hi>ſpare</hi> the <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, that <hi>exalt</hi> themſelves againſt <hi>Chriſt himſelfe? The Diſciple is not above his Maſter, nor the ſervant above his Lord,</hi> ſaith that <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſervants</hi> it is our honour to be. Now ſeeing there is a <hi>neceſſity</hi> laid upon the Prophets of Chriſt to <hi>plead</hi> their owne <hi>cauſe:</hi> Brethren, beare with me if I <hi>lay</hi> out a few <hi>ſands</hi> upon that <hi>ſervice,</hi> and <hi>ſacrifice</hi> a few <hi>words</hi> to the expected <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſure, prejudice,</hi> and <hi>miſinterpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of this <hi>Anti-miniſteriall</hi> generation. Mee thinkes 'tis a ſad thing Brethren, that thoſe Meſſengers of good tidings, and <note place="margin">This Intereſt was not ſo ſlighted as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</note> Ambaſſadours of peace, who not many yeares agoe you <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:112834:15"/> as <hi>Angels</hi> of God, nay even <hi>received</hi> as <hi>Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> of whom every one was no leſſe then a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Diana newly dropt from heaven</hi> in your eyes, are now become the <hi>off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcowring of all things, Antichriſtian Prieſts,</hi> and I know not what elſe the tongues of <hi>Sectaries</hi> will create them: That among all thoſe that complaine of <hi>perſecution,</hi> the Miniſters of the Goſpel only, though they moſt are, yet are ſcarce <hi>thought capable</hi> of <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſecuted:</hi> That among ſo many <hi>Pleas</hi> for <hi>Toleration</hi> of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Tis now.</note> thing, the <hi>Miniſteriall calling</hi> is only eſteemed <hi>intolerable:</hi> That every <hi>ſcurrilous Pamphleter</hi> dares make bold with our <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> and <hi>Perſons</hi> in <hi>Print,</hi> and proclaime to the world (to the diſgrace of our Church &amp; Nation) this <hi>news,</hi> that in <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> the rareſt Miniſtery in the Chriſtian world, is <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted</hi> without controule by the pens of ſuch <hi>mercenary Scriblers,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. cant.</hi> Creſ. Gram. lib. 3. <hi>Quid reſponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re poſſent non invenientes, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito crebrius, &amp; audacius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcellionum violentiis tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> furenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nos a praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canda Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licâ veritate ſua<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fallaciâ convincendá deterrere coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perunt.</hi>
               </note> that in divers places in the Kingdome, a godly Miniſter (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he can be ſo much ſheep himſelf, as to let his <hi>flock</hi> be <hi>worried</hi> before his eyes, and ſay, or do nothing) can ſcarce <hi>preach</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>tumults,</hi> or <hi>come abroad</hi> without <hi>threatnings;</hi> that wee have reaſon enough to feare ſuch uſage from ſome of thoſe <hi>ſticklers</hi> for <hi>confuſion</hi> in our times, as the Father complaines of in his, <hi>viz. That when they know not how to anſwer us, they will terrifie or knocke us out of our Arguments,</hi> when, (which God forbid) their <hi>party</hi> is ſo far <hi>Maſter</hi> of the <hi>power</hi> of the Kingdome as to <hi>dare at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">feared it may be more.</note>. And for my part, if they <hi>come</hi> once to that paſſe, I ſhal be <hi>ſorry</hi> to take the <hi>liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> they will then <hi>give</hi> me, who now plead moſt for it themſelves.</p>
            <p>And I pray what is the <hi>cauſe</hi> of all this <note n="b" place="margin">The preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for it.</note>? Truly they will tel us, they <hi>feare we will grow too high.</hi> And why is this feared? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would faine have <hi>Church-power</hi> diſpenced, as it was in its firſt <hi>inſtitution,</hi> before there were <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrates.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would faine keep <note n="c" place="margin">Examined, and ſome reall grounds diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> our <hi>Fatherly bowels,</hi> and not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to uſe our people, as the wicked Monke did King <hi>John,</hi> to <hi>give them poyſon in a Sacrament,</hi> becauſe wee deſire to have the power of <hi>Stewards</hi> (as we are) in the houſe of God, to ſee that <hi>none but our Maſters Family dyet at our Maſters Table.</hi> And I feare in this particular, he that feares a <hi>godly Miniſter</hi> would bee ſo <hi>high</hi> as to <hi>ſhut him out if</hi> he had ſuch a <hi>power</hi> allowed him, hath cauſe to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> himſelfe an <hi>Alien</hi> or a <hi>Dogge,</hi> not fit for that <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:112834:15"/> and I am confident if ſome of the maine <hi>Whiſperers of this jealouſie</hi> had windows in their breaſts, it would be found, their <hi>maine feare</hi> is, either that they ſhall be <hi>rejected</hi> as too bad, or elſe be <hi>enforced to become too good.</hi> It may be too our <hi>maintenance</hi> troubles others, who would be contented to <hi>ſhare ſtakes</hi> with us, to bring us <hi>lower.</hi> But me thinks they might remember how they ſped that ſaid in another caſe; <hi>Let us kill the heir that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance may be ours.</hi> It may be others think the people will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be brought to <hi>worſhip</hi> the <hi>Calves</hi> in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> to reliſh <hi>illiterate,</hi> and <hi>mechanicke Preachers;</hi> and the <hi>loweſt</hi> of the <hi>people</hi> will never paſſe for <hi>Prieſts,</hi> till the <hi>Prieſts</hi> (as they call them) be made the <hi>loweſt</hi> of the <hi>people.</hi> And it may be another ſort would faine bring the Ordinances of the Goſpell to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Law-benches, where they would make a ſhift to ſet us by the eares, and make us fee for our Sacraments, as they do for our eſtates.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you conſider, (eſpecially you in whoſe hands it is, <note place="margin">This Intereſt preſſed mainly upon Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment members.</note> to <hi>encourage</hi> us, or to <hi>perſecute</hi> us by a law) God calls to you this day, and this charge is yours, <hi>Do my Prophets no harme.</hi> I dare not think you wil <hi>vote</hi> us or <hi>enact</hi> us into a <hi>ſuffering condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for <hi>preaching</hi> to you, or <hi>praying</hi> for you. But however, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you beware how you come under being <hi>interpreted</hi> to <hi>doe</hi> ſo, by not <hi>forbidding</hi> them that would <hi>cruſhus,</hi> and to their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer do <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui non v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>care, cumpoſſit jubet.</hi>
               </note>. I do not readily remember any but <hi>wicked Princes</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ahab, Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam, Zedeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah. Naz.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (that Scripture records) that <hi>ſuffered</hi> good Prophets to be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before their <hi>faces.</hi> Let me tell you freely, the people are <hi>gone</hi> as <hi>far</hi> in harming Prophets, as they <hi>dare goe without</hi> you. Some will not <hi>heare</hi> them, except they may <hi>preſcribe</hi> to them. <hi>The ſheep</hi> (as the Father obſerves it, was an abſurdity of his time) <hi>feede their Shepheards.</hi> Every one that hath the <hi>gift of Arrogance</hi> and <hi>Ignorance</hi> enough (contrary to an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of your own) takes a liberty of <hi>lawleſſe propheſying,</hi> and by that practice (to al whoſe eyes a love of <hi>Anarchy</hi> hath not blinded) <hi>propheſies</hi> the <hi>ruine</hi> of this flouriſhing <hi>Church</hi> &amp; <hi>State,</hi> except your care timely prevent it. And what ſcorn is everywhere caſt by Sectaries of all ſorts not only upon all the <hi>Miniſtery of this Kingdom</hi> in <hi>generall,</hi> but upon an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> in w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> there is as much <hi>learning, holineſſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>gravity,</hi> as ever <hi>Europe</hi> (I think) could ſhevv in a like number
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112834:16"/> of men; and which ſit by your <hi>Authority,</hi> and therefore in <hi>equity</hi> ought to have your <hi>protection;</hi> you need goe no farther for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, then the late <hi>wholſome</hi> diſcovery of the <hi>poyſon</hi> of <hi>Aſpes</hi> under the <hi>lips</hi> of many of them, in the <hi>hiſtoricall</hi> part of <hi>Gangre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vid: Gangren. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> part 1 ecit: page, 155. 156.</note> What threatning <hi>ſpeeches</hi> have proceeded from ſome of them, (the true Image of their <hi>bloudy thoughts)</hi> are they not written in the <hi>Records</hi> of him to whom <hi>vengeance belongeth?</hi> The all-ſeeing God knows, what <hi>arrows</hi> and <hi>ſwords</hi> they continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſpeake,</hi> againſt the Prophets of the moſt High: and we make no queſtion will one day <hi>retort</hi> them into their own breaſts.</p>
            <p>Thus far they goe, and farther they would proceed, no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, (or elſe they ſtrangely degenerate from their <hi>Grandſires of Munſter)</hi> if you would but ſleep a little, and let them <hi>play</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> a while without <hi>controule.</hi> But God forbid that they ſhould ever proceed ſo far as to perſwade you to <hi>enable,</hi> or <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> them to <hi>act</hi> what they have in their <hi>thoughts,</hi> againſt thoſe without whom, neither they, nor your ſelves, had ever <hi>had</hi> the <hi>common enemy</hi> at ſuch a <hi>lift,</hi> as (God be bleſſed) you now <hi>have.</hi> I beſeech you pardon me this <hi>Character,</hi> and (ſeeing 'tis a <hi>plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Argument,</hi> which you have more then once bin urged with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for favour to the <hi>rabble</hi> of all ſorts of <hi>Sectaries, to minde you of the good ſuch and ſuch have done for you and the Kingdome,)</hi> give me leave a little to <hi>reflect</hi> upon the <hi>advantages,</hi> which by the means of the <hi>Miniſtery the Lord</hi> hath brought to the <hi>great worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay no more, but this. That the people <hi>offered</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo <hi>willingly</hi> to your aſſiſtance, that they <hi>contributed</hi> their eſtates ſo <hi>liberally,</hi> that they have <hi>adventured</hi> their <hi>lives</hi> ſo <hi>vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly,</hi> that they have <hi>borne</hi> the <hi>length,</hi> and <hi>chances</hi> of <hi>Warre</hi> ſo <hi>patiently, adhered</hi> to you ſo <hi>conſtantly,</hi> that the <hi>City</hi> hath <hi>aſſiſted</hi> ſo <hi>cordially,</hi> that our <hi>Brethren</hi> came to our <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> ſo <hi>readily,</hi> nay (let me add) that your <hi>owne hearts</hi> have been <hi>kept up</hi> ſo <hi>reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely;</hi> the main meanes under God, (I dare ſay) hath been the <hi>concurrence</hi> of the <hi>faithfull Prophets</hi> of God with you, in this <hi>worke.</hi> Far from my breaſt be the thought that they ſhall ever have cauſe to ſay with their Saviour: For <hi>which of theſe good works do you ſtone us?</hi> Nay, I hope that you will one day <hi>ſtop</hi> thoſe <hi>blacke mouths</hi> that <hi>raile</hi> at them, and <hi>puniſh</hi> thoſe that <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpightfully uſe</hi> them.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:112834:16"/>
            <p> I beſeech you that you will make ſome exemplary for rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at our Calling; and therein vindicate an Ordinance of your own; <note n="a" place="margin">The Ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for ordination after quoted.</note> ſee your own Ordinance put in execution, for the ſecuring of our Pulpits from the ſurprizall of every inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent mechanick; help us againſt the evil <hi>ſpirits</hi> of theſe days, that ſteale from us (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> complaines) our new-borne children, ere they can goe alone, and for the <hi>ſervice</hi> of their own <hi>belltes,</hi> make <hi>merchandize</hi> of their ſoules. <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſtianos quos maxime Chriſti nomine ſeducunt, jam per ipſius Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti Evange lium natos inveniunt &amp; faciunt illos divitias ſuas.</hi> Aug. 13. cont. Mani.</note> Helpe us againſt thoſe ſeeds-men of the evill one that creepe into houſes, and ſow <hi>tares,</hi> where 'tis not in our power (though never ſo watchfull) to prevent them. Suppreſſe thoſe ſet private meetings, in which theſe <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Prieſts vent their Myſtery of Inquity: and which they in divers places of this Kingdome altogether againſt the mind, and without the knowledge, and privity of the Paſtors, and at the time of publique Ordinances, frequent, and maintaine. Conſider I pray you what the Father ſaith in a like caſe; deſiring the Magiſtrate to ſuppreſſe <hi>Apollinarius</hi> his meetings. Hee poſitively affirmes that if they permitted ſuch Schooles of Errours, againſt their judgment, (for what ever ends of policy) it were in effect to <hi>proclaim their tenets orthodox, yea more orthodox then their own</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Naz. Orat.</hi> 46.</note>; and either they muſt know their errours, and permit them, or thinke them truths, and not embrace them; either of which I know not how a good Conſcience can brooke. <hi>It is a matter of great moment</hi> (ſaith <hi>Nazianzen) to reſtrain men from murther, and puniſh for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, but 'tis more to make lawes for the ſpreading and preſerving Religion, to bleſſe a people with ſound doctrine. Truly</hi> (as he goes on) <hi>the words of a Miniſter are not able to do ſo much, in conteſting for fundamentall truths</hi> [even for the <hi>holy Trinity</hi> it ſelfe, as he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in that place] <hi>as the commands of the Magiſtrate; if hee by authority ſtop the mouths of thoſe that are ſicke of ſuch hereticall infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, if he helps thoſe that are perſecuted by them, if he reſtraine the murtherers of ſoules, and keep poor ſoules from being murthered</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Naz. Orat.</hi> 31. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c &amp; infra.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Naz Orat.</hi> 31.</note>, his interpoſing may likely be a meanes effectuall, and powerfull to that purpoſe. But eſpecially look to it that there may bee no cauſe given from any carriage of any of you, to make faithfull Miniſters thinke, plaine truth will not bee as <hi>welcome</hi> to <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter now</hi> as <hi>heretofore,</hi> conſidering that you have ſo much
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112834:17"/> cauſe to thanke God, that in this great worke you have had ſo many <hi>plaine dealing</hi> Preachers about you, who have beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall to keepe up your ſpirits in the <hi>loweſt</hi> times, &amp; have continually <hi>adviſed</hi> you to thoſe wayes which God hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſo much ſucceſſe, eſpecially in the point of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> in the <hi>quarrell</hi> whereof you have ever ſince the day you tooke it (for the moſt part, conſtantly) <hi>proſpered;</hi> and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring too, that ſome that have Printed ſeditious, and traiterous <hi>Libels</hi> againſt you, are yet (as to any publike notice) <hi>unpuniſhed,</hi> one of them though queſtioned and in trouble, got too eaſily off.</p>
            <p>Conſider I beſeech you, God hath now wonderfully proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered you, and your Cauſe: Sure, there is no man will be ſo <hi>wicked</hi> as to <hi>perſecute</hi> his <hi>Miniſters in token of thankefulneſſe to him.</hi> If there be, let him conſider what God ſaith to his own people, when they bragged, God <hi>had delivered them to do all manner of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations,</hi> Jer. 7. 10. 12. 14, 15, 16. Neither will any (I hope) be ſo unmindfull of his <hi>Covenant</hi> (however ſome <hi>aequivocate</hi> in it <hi>groſſely)</hi> as to tolerate thoſe who muſt needs (according to their Hereticall and Schiſmaticall Principles) out of <hi>miſtaken</hi> conſcience <hi>perſecute Miniſters</hi> (as Chriſt ſaith ſome ſhould his Diſciples) <hi>and think they therein do God ſervice.</hi> What ſucceſs God hath given an handfull of them (among <hi>many thouſands of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe minded)</hi> in the <hi>Army,</hi> I hope ſhall be no ſtronger plea for an <hi>Antiminiſteriall,</hi> and <hi>haereticall,</hi> then it is for the <hi>ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and profane party;</hi> with which theſe, and all <hi>Armies</hi> (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally among the <hi>ordinary</hi> ſouldiers) muſt needs abound, &amp; who have had as large <hi>hand</hi> too in their <hi>ſucceſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſure, by the <hi>Covenant</hi> you may as lawfully ſuffer both, as <hi>either.</hi> I know there are thoſe here in this City, that would <note place="margin">Vide Maſter <hi>Burroughs</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicum. p. 130.</note> faine take an Argument from the ſucceſſes that God hath given to his <hi>owne cauſe,</hi> in the hands of <hi>differently</hi> affected perſons, to ſet God in the <hi>head</hi> of an <hi>heterogeneous body,</hi> made up of as diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>members,</hi> as <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Image was of differing <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls,</hi> I meane a party made up of all kinds of Sectaries. I hope they will conſider how the <hi>Cavalliers</hi> ſped, when upon their ſucceſſes, they <hi>blaſphemouſly</hi> vaunted, that <hi>God was turned Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier;</hi> and thereby be perſwaded to beware, how they (as <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly)</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:112834:17"/> thinke, <hi>he is now turned Sectary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Honourable Patriots give mee <hi>pardon</hi> for this digreſſion in point of <hi>Method,</hi> I aske <hi>none</hi> in point of <hi>matter.</hi> Nor indeed is it ſo altogether improper here. I am fully convinced, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you as nearly as the Text concerns you; ſeeing you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not harme Prophets more, then by making the <hi>perſecution</hi> of them <hi>legall;</hi> which you muſt needs do, if you make a Law to tolerate thoſe <hi>wayes,</hi> whoſe <hi>principles</hi> neceſſarily involve it.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not for <hi>idle, ignominious,</hi> or <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Miniſters that are called Miniſters <hi>in opprobrium Miniſterii,</hi> ſuch as drive the <hi>bloody trade of damning ſoules.</hi> Away to the <hi>dunghill</hi> with ſuch <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavory ſalt.</hi> They may be employed any where <hi>cheaper</hi> to the <note place="margin">Eo deteriores ſunt, quia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liores non ſunt, qui meliores eſſe debuerunt. Salv.</note> State that employes them, then in the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> Let their lot be <hi>ſo much</hi> the <hi>heavier,</hi> by <hi>how much</hi> they ſhould have beene <hi>better</hi> then they are, ſeeing they are <hi>ſo much the worſe,</hi> (as <hi>Salvian</hi> ſaith in another caſe) <hi>becauſe they are no better, who ſhould have been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> (I could wiſh they had not too many <hi>Patrons</hi> among thoſe, who thinke the continuing them, will ſo <hi>corrupt our governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to make a greater reſort to their ſeparated Congregations.)</hi> I thinke I ſpeake the thoughts of all the godly Miniſters in the land, they will be ſo far from charging you with <hi>harming</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets for <hi>puniſhing,</hi> and <hi>putting out</hi> theſe, that they will thinke no action of yours will do them more <hi>right,</hi> then <hi>freeing</hi> them from ſuch <hi>botches</hi> of that <hi>honourable calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe I plead for, are the <hi>faithful, Orthodox, able,</hi> and <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious</hi> Paſtors. Uſe them well, as you love your ſelves, and the Kingdome, which I am confident (if they <hi>periſh</hi> from the Land) will not long ſurvive them.</p>
            <p>And now a word to you of the City, and all that feare God, and heare me this day. The Lord be bleſſed, you have (for the moſt conſiderable part of you) been the <hi>ſhields and bucklers of the Prophets.</hi> And be you ſo ſtill. My Text hath a charge for you too. I hope you ſee how the Prophets Intereſt and yours are intwiſted each within the other. You cannot but know how ſoon <hi>Munſters</hi> calamity followed the perſecution of of its Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. You know how a <hi>community</hi> of propheſying there uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered in a community of eſtates, and plurality of Wives: and <hi>when</hi> their new-come Prophets had altogether expelled, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112834:18"/> their ſtanding Preachers; 'twas not long ere they fell to cut the throats, and rifle the houſes of the wicked; that is, all thoſe that had not loſt their <hi>Religion</hi> and their <hi>Wits</hi> like themſelves. <hi>Sleyden</hi> tells us that <hi>Thomas Muncer</hi> the fire-brand of <hi>Germany</hi> in its firſt Reformation, began thoſe Combuſtions by preaching againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> and cutting out a middle way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and the Pope, to make <hi>Luther</hi> as odious on one ſide, as the Pope on the other ſide <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sleid. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Com. Huc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcil. Alſtetum ubi eomnigra vit ille, coepit doce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re primum non ſolum adverſas p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ificem Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum, ſed ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum quoque Lutherum; u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſque doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam eſſe vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam &amp; impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note>. And a little after in <hi>Munſter</hi> 'twas voted an Ace beyond him, that of the two falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Luther, Luther</hi> was the worſt <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Id lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Comm. Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum etiam &amp; Pontificem Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum aiunt eſſe falſos Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetas. Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tamen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero deterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi>
               </note>. And what were the ſiſter opinions unto this; and into what confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they quickly reduced the whole City and Countrey by <hi>decrying</hi> the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> as much, the ſame Hiſtorian abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly relates. Sure, that <hi>Generation</hi> hath hitherto had <hi>like good will</hi> to both <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> power. I cannot but take notice that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.*<hi>Tombes</hi> in his late <hi>examination</hi> of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Marſhall's</hi> Sermon, (though he deny the <hi>neceſſary depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> of the reſt of thoſe <hi>Muncerian</hi> and <hi>Munſterian</hi> miſcarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, upon the opinion of <hi>Antipaedobaptiſme,</hi> in which point Maſter <hi>Marſhall</hi> hath anſwered ſufficiently, yet) taking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to lay downe ſome reaſons upon which it may ſeem no wonder, it was ſo accompanied in thoſe dayes: among the reſt, he alledgeth their <hi>want</hi> of a regular <hi>Miniſtery:</hi> and hence I believe I may be bold to argue thus far; that whatever Sects are enemies to a regular Miniſtery (as moſt of the Sectaries in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>But it is no marvaile that when men grow into Sects ſuch things happen, oſpecially when the Reformation of an abuſe is denyed in an orderly Synodicall way.</hi> [In which yet (referring to Munſter) Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> to excuſe the Anabaptiſts, without Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, croſseth the Hiſtory that <hi>Sleyden</hi> tells us, l. 10. that before the Magiſtrates of Munſter expelled them, by a Decree they allowed them a diſpute before them with the Miniſters, which as the place would permit was an orderly Synodicall way; and afterwards offered them another, before learned, and able Moderators, which <hi>Rotman</hi> refuſed] <hi>and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ſeek it declaimed againſt, accuſed, and accurſed, and perſecuted as Schiſmaticks, and Hereticks, and unlearned and factious men,</hi> [marke theſe words; this is the plaine ſtate of moſt of our Sectaries in England] <hi>joyne with a diſcontented party for finiſter ends, ſo that the men that hold an opinion have no regular Miniſtery nor orderly meetings to debate, or conclude of things among themſelves; and to agree upon a confeſſion of their Doctrine to be by all avouched.</hi> Tombs Examin. page 24. Sect. 5.</note> are, and moſt Anabaptiſts of any) 'tis no wonder if they bring themſelves, and the places where they are, into ſuch tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112834:18"/> and <hi>Antimagiſtraticall</hi> practiſes. And truely, 'tis no wonder to me, when I conſider that the <hi>Principles</hi> of their <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> to Miniſtery will eaſily be improved to an <hi>overthrow</hi> of <hi>Magiſtracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heare it I beſeech you, all you that love order; and believe it Citizens, (whoſe <hi>Government</hi> hitherto hath been your <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry)</hi> according to theſe mens <hi>principles,</hi> (as farre as they are pleaſed to diſcover them) you have no greater <hi>ſecurity</hi> for your <hi>ſword,</hi> or <hi>ſeat</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for your <hi>Chaines</hi> and <hi>Scarlet,</hi> then wee have for our <hi>Coats</hi> or our <hi>Pulpits.</hi> And ſure in their uſuall way of arguing, from a pretended <hi>flaw</hi> in our <hi>Calling,</hi> to a ſcorn of our <hi>Doctrine,</hi> a ſurprizall of our <hi>Office,</hi> and a perſecution of our <hi>Perſons;</hi> though they doe not mention you in their <hi>premiſes,</hi> yet they may in the <hi>Concluſion;</hi> ('Tis ordinary with their Sophiſtry, to bring more in the concluſion then is in the premiſes) and it will goe hard with them, if when they have begun with the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> they do not end with the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> &amp; when they have made the <hi>Miniſter good man Prieſt,</hi> they will bid faire to make my <hi>Lord, Mr. Major</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>And how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable this is ſee the diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation recorded in Gangraena.</hi> 2. <hi>Part. p.</hi> 17. <hi>where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſticall Diſputants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorded the Lord Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or, &amp; called him in ſcorne, Maſter Major.</hi>
               </note>. For let any man tell me in ſober ſadnes, whether by the <hi>Warrant,</hi> which they pretend from 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 10. they may not as wel make themſelves <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> as they conclude themſelves <hi>Preachers.</hi> I know not if a mans ſole gifts authorize him to teach (though not by vertue of any office, yet out of <hi>charity;</hi> as they diſtinguiſh moſt abſurdly, as if <hi>Charity</hi> would beare a man out in doing acts of office, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Commiſſion)</hi> why they may not be as <hi>charitable</hi> to the <hi>Lord Major and Court of Aldermen,</hi> as to us; eſpecially ſeeing the <hi>manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit withall:</hi> &amp; ſure there is a gift of <hi>Governing,</hi> as well as a gift of <hi>Prophecying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let any man againe reſolve me whether if <hi>[Be not Lords over Gods Heritage]</hi> exclude us from all <hi>power</hi> in the <hi>Church; [Call no man Maſter upon earth;</hi> and, <hi>Dare any of you goe to Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an Infidell, and not before the Saints]</hi> doe not ſhut you out from any in the <hi>State</hi> as well; eſpecially when they ſhall <hi>vote</hi> you <hi>Infidels</hi> (as the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> have moſt of you already in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect) and your Government to be after the <hi>manner of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> as they have us <hi>Anticriſtian,</hi> and our government <hi>tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:112834:19"/> Adde to this, that your governement in your <hi>Families</hi> hangs in the ſame ſtring; and why your <hi>ſervants</hi> may not take upon them to be your <hi>Maſters</hi> when they pleaſe, that is, when they are perſwaded they have a gift of <hi>governing</hi> better then you, I know not, if the former Argument be ſound: at leaſt, why not refuſe to call you Maſters, if the latter be valid.</p>
            <p>Conſider I beſeech you Citizens; you have <hi>borrowed</hi> from the whole <hi>Kingdom</hi> the choyſeſt <hi>Jewels</hi> they have. I believe you ſee, they will be called away from you faſt enough, now the Countrey is open againe: if upon their departure, you have a <hi>famine</hi> of the word, it will perhaps be a <hi>vexation</hi> of ſpirit to you to remember, if (which God forbid) you ſhould entreat theſe <hi>Joſephs</hi> ill while you have them, whom God hath <hi>ſent</hi> before to ſtore you, perhaps againſt ſuch a time.</p>
            <p>Sure it concernes you neerely to take that care for them which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth his <hi>Corinthians</hi> to take for <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 16. 10. that they <hi>may bee among you without feare; that no man deſpiſe them.</hi> Let them have no cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of <hi>London,</hi> as <hi>Salvian</hi> doth of <hi>Carthage: The Athenians</hi> and <hi>Lycaonians themſelves would heare Paul;</hi> But in <hi>Carthage</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſuch ſervants of God cannot bee ſeen in the ſtreets with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reproaches.</hi> Let not ſuch uſages be eſteemed no <hi>perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> becauſe 'tis not <hi>Man-ſlaughter;</hi> and faithfull <hi>Miniſtery</hi> the leſſe <hi>Martyrs,</hi> becauſe they are not <hi>murthered.</hi> Truely, that things are not come to that height, 'tis not becauſe the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors are not <hi>bloudy</hi> enough, but becauſe they are not <hi>Potent</hi> enough; <hi>and this kindneſſe is not the mens, but the Lawes</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Intra Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem appare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in plateis &amp; compitis Dei fervos ſine contumelia non licuit. Perſecutionem hanc ſuiſſe non putant, qui a non &amp; occiſi ſunt—ſed in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbe illa, non tam hominum fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hac beneficia, ſed legum. Salv.</hi> Another ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſse to all together, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Intereſt.</note>. My Lords, Commons, Citizens, Brethren, all that heare me this day; doe you thinke you have any greater <hi>Intereſt</hi> then your <hi>Religion?</hi> I am ſure you <hi>ſhould</hi> not; I hope you doe not. You are bid to <hi>contend earneſtly for the faith once delivered to the Saints</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Jude 5.</note>. As you love Religion look to the uſage of Gods Prophets. Were it not for them I know not, (things having been carried as they have (that I ſay no more) by ſome of the <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Martiall</hi> power) how many <hi>Articles</hi> of our <hi>Faith</hi> had remained <hi>unqueſtioned</hi> by this time. Neither doe I know yet, whether in their private Congregations by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112834:19"/> ſome or other, they be not all <hi>undetermined.</hi> I have cauſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve moſt are. But ſure, that they yet dare not <hi>outface the light,</hi> 'tis no ſmall fruit of the labours of the <hi>orthodox Prophets.</hi> Sure had our <hi>Pulpits</hi> (through our default) beene as open to them, as (by the fault of others) the <hi>Preſſes</hi> have, you had ſcarce (as far as ſome could prevaile to rob you of them) had, left you, a <hi>God,</hi> a <hi>Chriſt,</hi> an <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> a <hi>Word of God,</hi> a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> nay (you had been ſo far from being <hi>allowed</hi> to be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that) you had been <hi>denyed</hi> to be <hi>Men,</hi> and been <hi>unreaſonably</hi> ſcoft at for not <hi>renouncing</hi> your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Nay theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, theſe <hi>depths of Sathan</hi> are not yet <hi>ſounded</hi> to the <hi>bottome.</hi> They do not yet tell you when they will leave <hi>robbing</hi> you. The <hi>innumerable incomprehenſible Reſerve of New-light</hi> is the <hi>Gyges ring,</hi> by meanes whereof they walke in a <hi>cloud</hi> at noon-day, and keep their principles <hi>inviſible</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quotidie Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retici immuta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dogmata ſua. Deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſi vir Eccleſiaſticus de Scripturis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruditus conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit contra e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, &amp; Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſanctis coar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guerit eos, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim requirunt quomodo aliud novum dogma reperiant. Non quaerunt quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ſalventur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſed quomodo ſuperent.</hi> Hier. in Pſ. 5.</note>. <hi>To day they ſit with us and judge with us, if the great drivers of the deſigne, and leaders of the rabble ſo guide them: to morrow they ſit, and vote againſt us, if the wind turn; and (which is worſe) are not aſhamed to ſay and unſay before the ſame Auditors</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Naz. Orat. 32.</note>. <hi>&amp;c. Quo teneam vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus mutantem Protea nodo?</hi> Thus they <hi>ſhift</hi> tenets continually leſt you ſhould take <hi>hold</hi> of them; and when you thinke you have them at an advantage, they ſtep aſide behind ſome <hi>aequivocation</hi> or other, and leave a <hi>cloud</hi> in your <hi>Armes</hi> in ſtead of that you <hi>graſped</hi> at. Nor is this liberty taken only in things of <hi>ſmal</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, and of an <hi>indifferent</hi> nature. <hi>Here is the danger, and the wonder of it.</hi> There <hi>are as many Faiths abroad as fancies, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Faiths as deſtroy all faith; yea, concerning God himſelf, every year, may every moneth begets a new Creed, the new undermines the olde</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Periculoſum vobis at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> etiam mirabile eſt tot nunc fides exiſtere, quot voluntates, &amp;c. Sic plurimae coeperunt eſſe fides, ut nulla ſit; imo vero annuae, menſtruae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> de Deo fides de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ernuntur; novis ſubvertuntur vetera,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hilar. lib ad Conſtantium &amp; Conſt. Impp. de Arian.</hi>
               </note>. How (beloved) can you think it ſafe for <hi>Religion</hi> now, to part with your <hi>orthodox</hi> Prophets, that <hi>hold faſt the forme of ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and have learning enough to <hi>confute theſe gainſayers;</hi> for a rabble of <hi>bottomleſſe</hi> opinions, and opinioniſts: the workings
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112834:20"/> of whoſe fancies are as reſtleſſe, and more <hi>unbounded</hi> and <hi>irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> then the vaſt <hi>Occan,</hi> which hath its <hi>confines</hi> of motion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and an <hi>Huc uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> to put a <hi>ſtop</hi> to its <hi>proud waves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this I hope you ſee how greatly your ſelves, nay Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelfe, are <hi>Intereſted</hi> in the uſage of your Paſtors and Gods Prophets.</p>
            <p>And now I had done, had I not cauſe to thinke ſome cavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">An Appendix for the vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery againſt the common cavill that 'tis Antichriſtian, becauſe we had our Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from Prelates.</note> ſpirits, wovld thinke to receive the <hi>charge</hi> in the Text, &amp; yet ſave themſelves <hi>harmleſſe</hi> by queſtioning the <hi>application,</hi> as not belonging to the <hi>Miniſters of this Church;</hi> whom they will not own as men <hi>commiſſioned by God,</hi> but <hi>Emiſſaries of Antichriſt, and therefore unlawfully called.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could in the firſt place (but that the <hi>objecters</hi> and <hi>they</hi> in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things <hi>agree</hi> ſo well, that in <hi>this,</hi> there is little hope they will <hi>fall out)</hi> ſet <hi>them</hi> and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> by the eares about it. How ſaith the <hi>Jeſuite;</hi> are our Miniſters true Miniſters or no? No (ſaith he) <hi>for they have not a calling from the univerſall Biſhop.</hi> And how ſay you now Maſter <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> are our Miniſters true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or no? No (ſaith he) <hi>for they are ſent by the Pope of Rome, and ſo Anti-chriſtian.</hi> Friends agree among your ſelves, what to <hi>object,</hi> and we wil <hi>anſwer</hi> you both together; or <hi>fall out</hi> among your ſelves, and <hi>you</hi> will <hi>anſwer one another.</hi> But ſure as long as you ſtand thus <hi>oppoſite</hi> in your aſſertions, one muſt lye, and (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the world know's not which) they will caſt the lye at a venture, and truly ſpeake it <hi>handſomer,</hi> and call it <hi>aequivocation</hi> or <hi>mentall reſervation,,</hi> and you are <hi>both</hi> too well <hi>verſed</hi> in it to <hi>diſowne</hi> it.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall ſpeake a few words to the cavill itſelfe, and but a few; For I remember this is a <hi>Sermon,</hi> not a <hi>Treatiſe.</hi> To cleare <note place="margin">The objection anſwered to the Parliament from their own Ordinance for ordination of Miniſters, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring date, Oct. 2. 1644.</note> this particular, the <hi>ground</hi> of my exhortation to you, (my Lords and Gentlemen) I ſhall not need. I will not thinke you have ſet forth any thing as the reſult of both <hi>Houſes</hi> debates, which you were not fully ſetled in. Nor will I thinke you are ſo given to change, as to diſavow that now, which you have in a publique edict <hi>acknowledged.</hi> I read your ſenſe of this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in your <hi>Ordinance</hi> for <hi>Ordination,</hi> where in the <hi>Preamble</hi> you aſſert, <hi>That no man ought to take upon him the office of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter untill he be lawfully called, and ordained thereunto; that this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112834:20"/> (that is, an outward ſolemn ſetting apart of perſons for the office of the Miniſtery in the Church by preaching Preſbyters) is an Ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt. That thoſe who have been formerly ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Biſhops, (ſeeing that action was performed by them as Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, with the Aſſiſtance of other Preſbyters) have an Ordination for ſubſtance valid, and not to be diſclaimed by any that have received it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that 'tis the <hi>ſenſe of both Houſes,</hi> that our Ordination (as by Biſhops, the medium by which the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> prove us An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian) is notwithſtanding <hi>according</hi> to an <hi>Ordinance of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt for ſubſtance, and conſtitutes us Miniſters of the Church of Chriſt, and capable of giving a like miſſion to others.</hi> What there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>concerns</hi> you in the application of the charge in my Text, your own Ordinance faſtens on you, and I hope it ſhall never <hi>witneſſe</hi> againſt you. I perſwade my ſelfe, ſeeing you acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge us Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo Goſpell Prophets, to you I have not <hi>miſapplyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To you <hi>Citizens</hi> and fellow <hi>Brethren,</hi> I ſhall ſpeake as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely <note place="margin">To the reſt.</note> too as is poſſible. If you are <hi>converted to Chriſt,</hi> and not to <hi>opinion,</hi> you muſt needs come within the <hi>reach</hi> of the Apoſtles <hi>Argument.</hi> If theſe Miniſters be not <hi>Apoſtles to others,</hi> yet they <note place="margin">Diſcovering the undutifu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors (moſt of them) in ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecting. Queſtioning the conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
               <hi>are to you.</hi> For moſt of you are <hi>begotten by their Goſpell,</hi> and I hope no <hi>dutifull ſonne</hi> will charge his <hi>Father</hi> with <hi>illegitimation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To others who thus argue, our <hi>Miniſtery</hi> is <hi>derived from An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> that is, in their meaning, from Biſhops inſtalled by him, <hi>and 'tis therefore Antichriſtian;</hi> although the conſequence of that Argument be juſtly <hi>obnoxious,</hi> (for 'tis not being deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from perſons having an Antichriſtian <hi>power,</hi> that makes a thing Antichriſtian, unleſſe it can be proved that the thing ſo derived is <hi>derived</hi> by that Antichriſtian <hi>power;</hi> the <hi>ſame</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may act by a <hi>double</hi> power, a legall, and an <hi>uſurped</hi> power; now 'tis not argument enough to prove this or that act they doe is an illegall act, becauſe done by one that <hi>uſurps</hi> an <hi>illegall power,</hi> becauſe ſuch a perſon that hath a <hi>legall</hi> power too, may as well act by it; and this is in effect the Argument of the Parliament in the Ordinance before quoted) yet I paſſe this. And anſwer:</p>
            <p>The <hi>Antecedent</hi> cannot be <hi>proved,</hi> and 'tis only an <hi>affirmation,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Queſtioning the Antecedent upon good grounds.</note>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:112834:21"/> that our Miniſtery though conſecrated by Biſhops, was derived from Antichriſt. And it may be <hi>probable</hi> enough, and as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable (I am ſure) as any thing they can bring to the contrary; (which is enough to invalidate this Argument) that (though for <hi>ſome ages</hi> paſt, it were granted, that <hi>Biſhops</hi> inveſted by <hi>Popes,</hi> have been the <hi>Ordainers,</hi> and the Miniſtery hath had its ſucceſſion from them) that there vvas <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> long before <hi>Popery;</hi> and the Miniſtery then may be ſaid to be derived from <hi>beyond Popery;</hi> and 'tvvill be <hi>queſtionable</hi> vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther even thoſe Popiſh Biſhops did <hi>all</hi> or <hi>any</hi> of them <hi>originally</hi> receive their <hi>Preſbyterſhip</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> or from that <hi>ſucceſſion;</hi> though they received their <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> from <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, ſecondly, this Argument will caſt as ſtrong <hi>jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies</hi> upon the calling of <hi>all the preſent Miniſterie</hi> of all the <note place="margin">Shewing what miſchiefes this Argument in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves.</note> 
               <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> ſeeing Popiſh <hi>Ordainers</hi> have at one time or another <hi>interrupted</hi> the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Apoſtolicall ſucceſſion,</hi> and then it will inferre, that at preſent in all, and in moſt of <note n="1" place="margin">1. As ſtrong a ground of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of all the Miniſtery in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world at this time.</note> them for ſome ages, there hath been no <hi>Miniſterie;</hi> and ſo no lawfull <hi>Ordinances:</hi> and by the ſame Reaſon (as farre as we know the extent of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in the <hi>World)</hi> wee may argue in like manner, ſeeing Antichriſt hath had his <hi>claw</hi> in every <hi>corner</hi> of it at one time or another as it is more then probable. And ſo Chriſts <hi>Promiſe</hi> to bee with <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> and <hi>Baptizers</hi> (who muſt have a lawfull call to make them capable of that promiſe) <hi>to the end of the World,</hi> would at this time, (there being no lawfull called Teachers and Baptizers ſuppoſed in the world; by this Argument) be little better then concluded a <hi>falſehood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe thirdly, I know not what ſhould ſtop theſe men <note n="2" place="margin">2. A road-way to Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, Seeking, and that in <hi>infinitum.</hi>
               </note> from <hi>Anabaptiſme,</hi> or <hi>Sebaptiſme,</hi> if they be not infected yet; or <hi>Seeking</hi> if they be, that thus object. For I take their ſuppoſition, and thus argue; either the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> which they received from this <hi>Miniſtery</hi> was <hi>valid,</hi> or <hi>null;</hi> if <hi>valid,</hi> they deſtroy their <hi>poſition,</hi> that our <hi>Miniſterie is unlawfull</hi> (for no <hi>act of office</hi> (as adminiſtring a Sacrament) can bee <hi>valid</hi> from one that is not a <hi>lawfull Officer,)</hi> and I anſwer as the Father in a like caſe, <hi>I acknowledge this Miniſterie upon</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:112834:21"/> 
               <hi>the ſame grounds upon which they owne thoſe that are Baptized by it. And they prove them lawfull Miniſters by admitting thoſe whom they have Baptized.</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">A Luciferian is brought in by <hi>Hierome,</hi> arguing thus. <hi>Si Ariani haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tici ſunt, &amp; hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retici Gentiles ſunt, &amp; Ariani Gentiles ſunt; Si autem Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani Gentiles ſunt, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat nullam ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietatem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae eſſe cum Arianis,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>cum Gentilibus; manifeſtum eſt veſtram Eccleſiam quae ab Arianis,</hi> i. e. <hi>Gentilibus Epiſcopos ſuſcipit, non tam Epiſcopos ſuſcipere, quam de Capitolio Sacerdotes, ac per hoc Antichriſti magis Sinagoga, quam Chriſti Eccleſia debet nuncupari.</hi> (I repeat this the more large, becauſe it expreſſeth to the full all the cavills of theſe dayes againſt our Calling and Churches.) To which the Father anſwers. <hi>Si Ariani (ut dicis) Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſunt, &amp; Arianorum conventicula caſtra ſunt Diaboli; quomodo in-caſtris Diaboli Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizatum recipis? &amp; infra. Tu enim Epiſcopum probas, quia ab eo recipis bptizatum.—ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ratione Epiſcopum ab Arianis recipio qua tu recipis baptizatum.—Quare ergo a nobis parietibus ſepararis, cum in fide, &amp; Arianorum nobiſcum receptione conſentias?</hi> Heir. adv. Lucif.</note>. If <hi>invalid;</hi> then they muſt bee <hi>baptized againe,</hi> if they will keep any <hi>Church-fellowſhip;</hi> and then they muſt either <hi>baptize themſelves,</hi> (contrary to the <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> and all examples of <hi>Scripture)</hi> or be <hi>Baptized</hi> by others: and how ſhall they bee aſſured of their <hi>Calling,</hi> or <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to whom they addreſſe themſelves, ſeeing even they alſo muſt be faine, either to derive it from one of theſe <hi>Miniſters,</hi> or thoſe that were <hi>Baptized</hi> by them; (and ſo the Argument touches them here againe) or <hi>themſelves.</hi> And hee that <hi>queſtions</hi> thus farre is to <hi>ſeek</hi> indeed, and may, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing I know be a <hi>Seeker in infinitum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I forget that this muſt not bee a Treatiſe, but a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: onely this I have added to ſtop the <hi>mouthes</hi> of ſome that perhaps would have ſhifted all the reſt off from their backs, if they had <hi>miſſed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To returne to you (beloved) and end in a few words: I <note place="margin">Concluſion.</note> beſeech you doe not onely <hi>not harme</hi> your Miniſters, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them, and aſſiſt them. You have <hi>Covenanted,</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>root out all Errour, Hereſies, Schiſme, Prophaneneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> but to <hi>aſſiſt all that doe ſo. Aſſiſt</hi> your Miniſters, whoſe <hi>maine worke</hi> it is. They have well led you the <hi>way,</hi> (you of the City eſpecially) by <hi>repreſenting the evills of Toleration;</hi> ſecond them in this.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:112834:22"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Petition</hi> for <hi>renewing the Ordinance for Ordination,</hi> that you may have a greater <hi>ſupply</hi> of ſuch Prophets, and <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> too.</p>
            <q>—<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſimili frondeſcat virga metallo.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Still <hi>ſeeke</hi> out and puniſh <hi>irregular Aſſemblies,</hi> and <hi>ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Preachers and Practiſers,</hi> and feare not the <hi>Bug-Beare</hi> word of <hi>Pehſecuting Saints,</hi> when they are out of the way of <hi>Saints.</hi> This doe, <hi>And the good hand of the LORD hee upon you for good.</hi> If this <hi>Exhortation</hi> bee any way <hi>beneficiall,</hi> I have my <hi>end,</hi> let <hi>God</hi> have the <hi>Glory;</hi> if not, I have done my <hi>Duty;</hi> and if Prophets <hi>fare ill,</hi> after ſuch a <hi>warning,</hi> by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing, or neglect of any of you, who ever you be that that <hi>heard,</hi> or <hi>reade,</hi> this Sermon; I aſſure my ſelfe it will bee a <hi>record</hi> againſt you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>REader, ſeeing the Author, by reaſon of his diſtance from <hi>London,</hi> and abſence from the preſſe, thereby occaſioned, could not be afore-hand with the Printer in preventing ſome miſtakes, he is forced to ſet theſe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand intimations heer, or to prevent thine.</p>
            <p>Page 1. Branch the Analyſis according to the ſence, (ſome particulars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miſcarryed by the reference. p. 6. at <hi>[Take, &amp;c.]</hi> ſhould bee inſerted that which p. 7, 8. is ſo incloſed []. p. 8. conceive the quotation in the Margin above the <hi>ibidem.</hi> p. 17. dele with. l. 11. p. 28. r. uſage; it, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. p. 29. undermined. p. 32. l. 1. r. conferred. infr. lawfully called.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:112834:22"/>
            <p> REader, thou art preſented with Apples of Gold, in Pictures of Silver; a Treatiſe in Vindication of the Miniſtrie, from baſe aſperſions daily caſt upon their Perſons, their Calling. It is no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to us to be accounted the filth of the World, the off-ſcowring of of all things; the Apoſtles were ſo, and Chriſt our Maſter; But there is no ſmall danger to thee to account us ſo: If it be the <hi>great Intereſt</hi> of States to protect the <hi>Saints;</hi> it is of farre greater concernment to doe the <hi>Prophets no harme.</hi> Theſe things were preached, now printed, not to <hi>ſhame,</hi> but <hi>warne</hi> thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Imprimatur, JA: CRANFORD.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sempt.</hi> 7. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
